<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plain and rational vindication of the liturgy of the Church of England collected out of the discourses of some of the reverend bishops and doctors of the same church, by way of question and answer / by J. Clvtterbvck, Gent.</title>
            <author>Clutterbuck, J. (John)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35618</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15500956</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15500956</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103580</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1185:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plain and rational vindication of the liturgy of the Church of England collected out of the discourses of some of the reverend bishops and doctors of the same church, by way of question and answer / by J. Clvtterbvck, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Clutterbuck, J. (John)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[6], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Keblewhite ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An account of the titles of all the books of the Old and New Testament and why they are stil'd canonical ... ": p. 58-66.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103580:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Plain and Rational VINDICATION and EXPLANATION OF THE LITURGY OF THE <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> Collected out of the Diſcourſes of ſome of the Reverend Biſhops and Doctors of the ſame CHURCH, by Way of QUESTION and ANSWER. By <hi>J. CL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TTERB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CK,</hi> Gent. <hi>The Second Edition with Improvements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Keblewhite,</hi> at the <hi>Swan</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1699.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:103580:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103580:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To my Beloved Daughters,</hi> SARAH LILLINGSTON <hi>AND</hi> MARY LEACH.</head>
            <p>THE Church's aim in all her Services was to make them reaſonable; and therefore, ſhe hath not only put them in a known Tongue, but alſo inſtructs us in the Nature of them, making her Prayer-Book a Sum of Divinity; but becauſe we are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into an Age, that many (who call themſelves Saints) do actually mock and ridicule her ſacred Offices: It's ſurely a Duty incumbent on all her Obedient Children, to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Honour of their Holy Mother the Church.</p>
            <p>I thought it therefore Time not ill ſpent (having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired my ſelf to a Private Life) to collect ſuch Reaſons out of the Writings of the Reverend Biſhops and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as may juſtifie not only her Commands, but enforce our Obedience to her Pious Edicts, and to the Obſervance of her lawful Ceremonies: And that my Affection may laſt longer than my Life, I preſent ye with theſe my Firſt-Fruits, hoping, that not only the Example and conſtant Practice of your Ancient Father, but his Advice and Counſel, may prevail with you to perſevere to the End, in the Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of that Church in which ye have been Baptized, Educated and Inſtructed, and let not Men deceive you with vain Words.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:103580:3"/>
            <p>I only at Firſt, deſigned theſe Collections for my own private Satisfaction, but I was prevailed upon by ſome Friends to make them Publick; for this Reaſon, becauſe they aſſured me they would be of Uſe and Advantage to thoſe of the meaner Underſtanding, and not deſpiſed by others that knew them already; which I chuſe to ſay that I may prevent the Cenſure of thoſe that may think this Publication proceeds from an itching Deſire of Applauſe, or at leaſt from Vain-Glory.</p>
            <p>Let not the Meanneſs of my Performances leſſen your Reverence to the Holy Offices of our Church, but live in the conſtant Uſe and Practice of them, and the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, will bleſs you both in Soul and Body, guiding ye by his Counſel here, and bringing ye at laſt to his Glory; which is the hearty Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Affectionate Father, J. CLUTTERBUCK.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>April</hi> 16. 1694.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103580:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>IT is obſerved by a Reverend and Judicious Author (Dr. <hi>Jo. Cockburn)</hi> That Early Buds are wont to pleaſe the curious who are generally a little impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient; But the Trees flouriſh beſt, and are moſt fruitful, which do not over-haſtily put forth before their proper Seaſon. This Obſervation had I duly conſidered, I ſhould not (to ſatisfie the importunity of ſome Friends) ſo haſtily have Publiſhed my Firſt Thoughts; However it appears that my Intentions to do good have been kindly received, the Firſt Edition being Sold off; and being hereby encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to a Second Impreſſion of this Book, and deſirous to have it more Correct and Uſeful; I have made ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Enlargements, in giving a ſhort Explication of the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> and the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> that all may underſtand what they Pray for and Read. This I am ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible is very excellently perform'd by ſeveral Eminent Hands, but I ſubmit to the Judgment of ſome worthy Friends, That I ought to conſult the Reader's Eaſe and Conveniency, and not to referr him altogether to what Others have writ. Several Remarks and Obſervations you will meet with in this Edition, which eſcaped my firſt Conſideration.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, I have given ſome brief Hints of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and Deſign of each Book of Holy Writ, which may in ſome meaſure aſſiſt in Reading thoſe Sacred Pages.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:103580:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>The Compilers of the Engliſh COMMON-PRAYER-BOOK were,</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Cranmer, <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>Mart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Goodrick, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Ely.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Skip, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Hereford.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Thirlby, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Weſtminſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Day, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Chicheſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Holbeck, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Lincoln.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Ridley, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rocheſter; after <hi>Biſhop of</hi> London, <hi>Mart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Cox, <hi>King</hi> Edward<hi>'s Almoner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Taylor, <hi>Dean of</hi> Lincoln, <hi>Mart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Heynes, <hi>Dean of</hi> Exeter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Redman, <hi>Dean of</hi> Weſtminſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Robinſon, <hi>Archdeacon of</hi> Leiceſter.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>May</hi> 1549. <hi>Anno Reg.</hi> Edw. 6. <hi>Tertio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh Reformation</hi> is the moſt compleat and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in its Kind, as retaining the moſt ancient Doctrine and ſoundeſt Confeſſion of Faith, founded upon the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and agreeable to the firſt General Councils, the moſt Primitive Church Government, and a Liturgy the beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to reconcile and unite Mens Devotions: Such a Liturgy, as Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> the Author of the Martyrology is not afraid to ſay was indited by the Holy Ghoſt; but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly had a great Teſtimony in the unſpeakable Joy and Contentment holy Men took in it in K. <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's days, their Zeal for the Maintenance of it, longing for the Reſtitution of it, and Sealed it with their Blood in Q. <hi>Maries</hi> days, and the Univerſal Triumphs and Acclamations at the Reſtoring of it in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Goodman <hi>Comp. Inquiry.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103580:4"/>
            <head>OF THE CALENDAR, AND THE <hi>Special USE thereof</hi> IN THE CHURCH of GOD.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Calendar</hi> of the Church is as full of Benefit as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, unto ſuch as are given to the ſerious Study and due Contemplation thereof; for beſides the admirable Order and Diſpoſition of Times, which are neceſſary for the better tranſacting of all Eccleſiaſtical and Secular Affairs; it hath in it a very Beautiful Diſtinction of the Days and Seaſons, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome are choſen out and ſanctified, and others are put among the Days of the Week to number.</p>
            <p>But the chief Uſe of it in the Church of God, is to preſerve a ſolemn Memory, and to continue in their due Seaſon, ſometimes a weekly, and ſometimes an Annual Commemoration of thoſe excellent and high Benefits which God hath beſtowed upon Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind for the Founding and Propagating of that Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which we now profeſs; together, with a Direction how to find the Leſſons, which the Church orders to be read every Day in the Week, at Morning and Evening Prayer.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the Multitude of Holy Men and Women became ſo exceeding numerous, that all the Days of the Year would not have been ſufficient for a ſeveral Commemoration of them, it was the great Wiſdom and Moderation of thoſe Religious, Grave Prelates, who did reform ſuch things as were many ways amiſs among us, to chuſe One Solemn Day alone, wherein to magnifie God for the Generality of all his Saints together, and to retain ſome few ſelected Days in every Month, for the Special
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103580:5"/> Memory of ſome Holy Perſons and Actions, hereby avoiding only the Burthen and the unneceſſary Number of Feſtival Days.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Golden Number and Dominical Letter.</head>
               <p>THE Golden Number was anciently deviſed to find out the Eccleſiaſtical beginning of the Year which always happen'd between <hi>March</hi> the <hi>7th.</hi> and <hi>April</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is ſo call'd, becauſe it was written in the <hi>Calendar</hi> with Letters of Gold, right on the Day whereon the Moon chang'd, and is the ſpace of 19 Years, in which the Moon returneth to the ſelf-ſame Day of the Year of the Sun, and therefore is alſo call'd <hi>the Cycle of the Moon,</hi> in which the <hi>Solſtices</hi> and <hi>Equino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctials</hi> do return to all one Point in the <hi>Zodiack.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To find it every Year, you muſt add One Year to the Year of Chriſt (for Chriſt was Born one Year of the 19 already paſt) then divide the whole by 19, and that which reſteth is the <hi>Golden Number</hi> for that Year, if there be no Surpluſage, it is then 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> That the <hi>Golden Number</hi> and <hi>Dominical Letter</hi> does change every Year the Firſt day of <hi>January.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Dominical Letter</hi> is ſo call'd, becauſe it ſhews the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical</hi> or <hi>Lord's-Day,</hi> throughout the whole Year.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note</hi> alſo, That the Year of our Lord beginneth the <hi>25th.</hi> day of <hi>March,</hi> the ſame Day ſuppoſed to be the Firſt Day upon which the World was Created, and the Day when Chriſt was conceived in the Womb of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103580:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Plain and Rational</hi> VINDICATION <hi>and</hi> EXPLANATION <hi>of the Terms, Order and Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of the</hi> LITURGY <hi>of the</hi> Church <hi>of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>by Way of</hi> Queſtion <hi>and</hi> Anſwer.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY are the Prayers and Publick Services of God ordered to be offered up in the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To offer up to God Publick Service in ſeparate and dedicated Places, (which we call Churches) is moſt fit for the Honour of God, (who ought to have a Place ſet apart for his particular Worſhip, which is not to be Profan'd by any common and ordinary Uſe, as being the Preſence-Chamber of the great King, where he is in the midſt of thoſe that meet in his Name) and our own Profit, for it begets and nouriſheth a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Awe to God and his Service, and warns us to put off our Shooes when we are upon Holy Ground, and ſo helps Devotion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we uncover our Heads when we firſt enter into the Church, and continue ſo before, and after the Prayers are begun and ended?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is out of Reverence to Him to whom thoſe Places are devoted, and in Memory of thoſe Spiritual Feaſts which we or our Chriſtian Brethren have there taſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Hath our Lord appointed this Publick Service and Worſhip called the Liturgy, under the Goſpel?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He hath only appointed the Materials and Eſſentials in general, <hi>viz.</hi> Prayers, Praiſes, and Confeſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But for the Manner, and Order, and Method, he hath left to be ordered and appointed by the Church, St. <hi>John</hi> 20. 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is the Publick Worſhip of God preſcribed by thoſe to whom he hath given Commiſſion, the only true and right Worſhip?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes: And all other Forms and Methods offered up in ſtead of that, though never ſo exactly drawn, are ſtrange Worſhip becauſe not commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> called Common-Prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe all the Members have a common Intereſt, and in that Form all of the ſame Communion are obliged to join.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What's the Meaning of the Word Liturgy?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A Form of Publick Prayers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is Prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Prayer is the lifting up of the Soul to converſe with God, always in Heart and frequently with the Tongue, offering up
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103580:6"/> our Confeſſions and Requeſts together with our Prayers and Thankſgivings in behalf of our ſelves or others, in deprecating of Evils, or ſupplicating for good things Spiritual or Temporal, and a Means to obtain all Bleſſings: It is an high Honour and huge Advantage to us, and is accepted by him as an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of his Authority, and a Teſtimony of our Obſervance.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or in fewer words, Prayer is an earneſt Requeſt to God in the Name of Chriſt for all things neceſſary for Soul or Body, our Selves or Others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Sentences out of the Holy Scripture uſed before we begin in the Morning and Evening Service?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Imitation of the Ancient People of God, who when they went into their Synagogues to pray, ſtood ſilent a while, to meditate before whom they ſtood; and theſe are choſen by the Church to be Admonitions to Repentance, the better to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare peoples hearts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Benefit do we reap, by coming to Church before the Prayers begin?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We may find among thoſe Sentences a Meditation fitted for our preſent frame of Spirit, in order to the better diſpoſing us to pray with true Devotion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> There are Variety of Diſpoſitions, and the ſame Man is not always in the ſame Temper; and becauſe every Man beſt knows his own Eſtate, be pleaſed to put thoſe Sentences of one kind together, in order to ſo good a Work.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Firſt Rank may conſiſt of thoſe Sentences which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſupport for the Fearful, to prevent that exceſſive Dread of God's Wrath, which hinders the Exerciſe of a ſprightly De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, by too much dejecting the Spirit. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51. 9. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 143. 2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 24.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Second Rank concerns thoſe that doubt of God's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which ſhow how fit they are to ask, and how likely God is to grant, upon their Repentance, notwithſtanding their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, <hi>viz. Pſ.</hi> 51. 17. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 10. St. <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. 18, 19.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Third Rank concern the ignorant, who either think they have no Sin, or that a ſlight Repentance will procure Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, <hi>viz.</hi> 1 St. <hi>John</hi> 8. 9. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. 27.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Fourth Rank are for the Negligent, who deferr this Duty of Repentance, <hi>viz. Pſ.</hi> 51. 3. St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 3.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Fifth Rank are for thoſe, who by Cuſtom grow Cold and Formal, <hi>viz. Joel</hi> 2. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What mean we by Gracious and Merciful in this laſt Sentence?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By Gracious we underſtand, He's ready to give, and by Merciful, He's apt to forgive.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:103580:6"/>
               <head>Of the Exhortation.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHAT is the Exhortation deſigned for?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To apply and ſet home the preceeding Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, and to direct us how we ought to perform the following Confeſſion: It collects the Neceſſity from the Word of God, it inſtructs us in the right Manner, when it hath convinced us that we muſt do it, and gives us the Reaſons why we muſt confeſs and repent ſincerely, juſt now; and then it invites us to that neceſſary Duty for which it hath ſo well prepared us; ſo that it connects the Sentences and the Confeſſion, making thoſe ſo uſeful, in order to this, that whoever hears them and conſiders the Inferences here made, cannot but be rarely diſpoſed for a Devout Confeſſion; and by this we may perform each Part of the Office with the Spirit, and with the Underſtanding alſo.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Daily Confeſſion.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is the Confeſſion to be ſaid after the Miniſter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To teſtifie our Conſciouſneſs of Guilt, to take Shame to our ſelves, and give Honour to God; and That (ſince we are all Sinners) our Repentance may be as publick as our Faults have been.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Church begin her Service with Confeſſion of Sin?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Sins unrepented of hinder the Succeſs of our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; when the Guilt is removed by penitential Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, there is no Bar to God's Grace and Mercy; ſuch as would pray effectually have always begun with Confeſſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How many Parts doth the Confeſſion conſiſt of?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Four: 1. An Introduction which ſets God before us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der two proper Titles, <hi>viz. Almighty and moſt Merciful;</hi> the Firſt to ſhow his Power, and ſtrike us with a holy Fear of his Anger; the Second to manifeſt his Love, and melt us with the Senſe of his Mercy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It conſiſts of an humble Confeſſion concerning the Manner of our Sinning, and of the Nature and the Effect of our Sins, <hi>viz. We have erred</hi> by ſudden, leſſer, and unobſerved Sins, and ſometimes <hi>ſtrayed</hi> farther out of the Ways, which God preſcribes, by willful, groſs, and cuſtomary Tranſgreſſions; ſo that we are become <hi>like loſt Sheep,</hi> helpleſs and expoſed to many Dangers, and of our ſelves, are as well unable as unlikely to return to <hi>Jeſus,</hi> the good Shepherd of our Souls.</p>
                  <p>We have improved our Original Corruption, which is here properly expreſſed by <hi>the Devices and Deſires of our own hearts,</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:103580:7"/> which we have followed, not checking them, but too often ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling them; and then they produce Actual Sins, which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs under the general Phraſe of our <hi>Offending againſt his holy Laws:</hi> And that we may be more particular, we reduce our Actual Sins to two ſorts, Sins of Omiſſion and Commiſſion. And then the Effect of Sins is expreſſed by that Phraſe, <hi>There is no Health in us;</hi> that is, no means of Help or Salvation in us, or, we are full both of Spiritual and Bodily Infirmities, ſo that there is no ſound Part in us.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It conſiſts of an earneſt Deprecation, containing the Evils we would be delivered from, <hi>viz.</hi> The Guilt of Sin, the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Power of it, and the Ground on which we hope to prevail.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Confeſſion conſiſts of a devout Petition, intimating to whom we pray, and for what we pray, and to what end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> In what Words do we pray, that the Guilt of Sin may be taken away?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In thoſe Words; <hi>Have mercy upon us, miſerable Offenders, viz.</hi> Pity and pardon us by taking away the Guilt of our Sins.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> In what Words do we pray to be delivered from the Puniſhment of our Sins?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In thoſe Words: <hi>Spare thou them, O Lord, who confeſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> In what Words do we pray to be delivered from the Power of Sin?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In thoſe Words: <hi>Reſtore thou them that are penitent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Ground on which we hope to prevail?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Promiſes declared in his Goſpel through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> To whom do we pray for Grace?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To God the Father, through <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> For what do we pray?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For Piety towards God, Juſtice and Charity towards our Neighbours, Sobriety and Temperance for our ſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> To what end?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To the Glory of God's holy Name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we ſay <hi>Amen?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To teſtifie our deſire to have all theſe Petitions granted, our faith in the Promiſes, and our hope of Acceptance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Confeſſion and our Prayers to be ſaid kneeling?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That we may expreſs the Humbleneſs of our Minds by the Poſture of our Bodies, which is the fitteſt for Penitents.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Abſolution.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is the Word <hi>Prieſt</hi> uſed by our Church in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Engliſh Word by a Contraction of the Syllables
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103580:7"/> has its Derivation from <hi>Presbyter,</hi> and according to the Latin Word <hi>Sacerdos,</hi> ſignifies him whoſe mere Charge and Function is about holy things; and therefore ſeems to be a moſt proper Word when he's in the Actual Adminiſtration of holy things.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, It is not a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Name, that is, not peculiar to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Miniſtery, but common to others, and frequently uſed by the Primitive Chriſtians; and by which the Prophets foretold, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhould be called, and by which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them, and by which our Saviour is in a multitude of places ſtyl'd and named the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> of our Profeſſion, and by which we are call'd, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. 6. and therefore may lawfully, ſafely, and without any juſt ground of Offence, be uſed by Chriſtians as a Name for the Miniſters of the Goſpel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why muſt the Prieſt pronounce the Abſolution ſtanding?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is an Act of Authority which is ſo to be done.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Can Man forgive Sin?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> God alone can exerciſe this Power in his own right, but he may and hath committed it to others; who do it in his Name, and by his Authority, in the Perſon of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Form of Abſolution is this?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is Declaratory, which is no more than the ſolemn pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of a Pardon, upon the Conditions of Faith and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and it is for the Satisfaction of truly Penitent Sinners, that our Church approves of applying the promiſes of Pardon in Scripture, to the particular caſe of thoſe Perſons, which is that we mean by Abſolution.</p>
                  <p>But if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend they can Abſolve whether God will or no, we muſt leave God and them to diſpute that Point. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Stillingfleet, <hi>on</hi> Idol. <hi>p.</hi> 159.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What other Forms of Abſolution are there in the Liturgy?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Two: One is Petitionary, in the Communion Service; the other is Judiciary, in the Office for the Sick. All theſe Forms in Senſe and Vertue are the ſame, being ſeveral Expreſſions of the ſame thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Muſt the People ſay the Words of the Abſolution after the Prieſt with an audible Voice?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: Becauſe it is the Privilege and Property of his Office to pronounce it. But our Hearts muſt be intent upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, and our Souls muſt embrace the Comforts, and we muſt ſeal all with <hi>Amen:</hi> To teſtify how firmly we believe, highly value, and earneſtly deſire thoſe Comforts. The latter part is an Application directing us what to Ask, and ſhewing us what are the Benefits of being Heard.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or in the Judgment of ſome Learned Perſons, it is Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary, in which we muſt joyn, <hi>Wherefore we beſeech thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:103580:8"/>
               <head>Of the Lord's Prayer.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is the Lord's Prayer united to all the Offices?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To make up their Defects, and to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them to our Heavenly Father, who cannot deny us, when we ſpeak the ſame Words which his dear Son hath put into our Mouths; this Prayer being the Foundation and Perfection of all Prayers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What did our Lord intend it for?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not only, for a Pattern to make other Prayers by, but for a form to be uſed in ſo many Words; for when he delivered it the ſecond time, he ſays expreſly: <hi>When you pray, ſay,</hi> S. <hi>Luke</hi> 11. 1. The delivery of the <hi>Lord's Prayer</hi> by St. <hi>Luke</hi> is not the ſame with that related by St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> but another, at another time, and upon another occaſion; whence it follows, That the Diſciples when it was firſt uttered, underſtood not that their Maſter intended it for a Form of Prayer to them, but for a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern or Example only; or it may be to inſtruct them in ſpecial in what manner to ask forgiveneſs of Sins; for if they had thought he had given them a Form of Prayer, then they would not have asked him for one now: Wherefore our Saviour this ſecond time uttered himſelf more expreſly.</p>
                  <p>Thus their Inadvertency becomes our Confirmation, and the Delivery of this Prayer was doubled to his Diſciples, That they and we might hereby know more certainly that our Saviour in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and commended it for a ſet Form of Prayer unto his Church. <hi>Joſ. Meedes</hi> Diatr. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Reaſon may be given that the Phraſes and particular Sentences are taken out of thoſe Forms, which were in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe among the Jews in our Saviour's time?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew that our Lord liked not uneceſſary Novelty in Prayer. <hi>Vide</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond,</hi> Dr. <hi>Comber.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Lord's Prayer called a perfect Form?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it comprehends Petitions ſuitable to all our Wants and intimates all our duty, and was drawn up by our glorious Advocate, who knew his Father's Treaſures as well as our Wants.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the People commanded to ſay the Lord's Prayer after the Prieſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we do thereby not only declare our Chriſtian Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but we do alſo the greater honour to God and our Bleſſed Saviour, by repeating it in the moſt Solemn manner we are able, and by our Fervency and Devotion therein, we edify our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. What are the Parts of this Prayer?</head>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:103580:8"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, A Preface, expreſſing the Goodneſs and Greatneſs of him to whom we pray.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Seven Petitions: But by many Learned Perſons, they are accounted to be but Six, the two laſt, <hi>Lead us not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But deliver</hi> being reckoned to be but one, as relating in both Parts to one another. The firſt three concerning God's Glory, <hi>viz.</hi> the Honour of his Name, the Advancement of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the fulfilling of his Will: And the four laſt Petitions concern our own good, <hi>viz.</hi> For temporal Supplies, for Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Sins paſt, for prevention of future Sins, and for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from Puniſhment.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, A Doxology aſcribing to God Dominion and Might, Mercy and Praiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Preface to the Lord's Prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our Father which art in Heaven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the Preface direct us in?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To pray unto God as our Father in Chriſt, and therefore willing to help us.</p>
                  <p>2. As in Heaven, and therefore able to help us.</p>
                  <p>3. To Pray with and for others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the meaning of the firſt Petition, <hi>viz.</hi> Hallow'd be thy Name?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the Name of God, is meant not only his Eſſential Name, which is Himſelf, as known to us in his Titles and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, but whatſoever is call'd by his Name and belongs to him, as his Word, his Worſhip, his Miniſters, with the Places, Times and Things dedicated to his Service; and by Hallowing is meant, That all theſe may be treated with reverent Regards for his Sake, and eſteem'd far above common things, and we deſire that God would enable us and others, in every thing to glorify and honour him above all, in Heart, Word and Deed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we Pray for in the ſecond Petition, <hi>viz.</hi> Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom come?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That Satan's Kingdom may be deſtroy'd, and that God's Kingdom of Grace may be advanc'd, by bringing us and others into it, and by keeping us all in it, and that his Kingdom of Glory may be haſten'd,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we Pray for in the third Petition, <hi>viz.</hi> Thy Will be done in Earth as it is, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That God would make us and others able and willing to obey his Word, and to ſubmit to his Will in all things, and both theſe with the like Chearfulneſs, Sincerity and Conſtancy as the Angels in Heaven.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we Pray for in the fourth Petition, <hi>viz.</hi> Give us this day our daily Bread?</head>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103580:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That upon our lawful Endeavours we may of God's free Gift receive a competent Portion of the good things of this Life, with all things needful both for our Souls and Bodies, and may enjoy God's Bleſſing with them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we Pray for in the fifth Petition, <hi>viz.</hi> Forgive us our Treſpaſſes as we, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That through the Satisfaction of Chriſt, we and others may be acquitted both from the Guilt and Puniſhment of Sin, and we pray God to forgive us, as we forgive our Offenders, that our forgiving them may be an Argument to God to forgive us, and an Obligation to our ſelves ſtill to forgive others, that God may ſtill forgive us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we Pray for in the laſt Petition, <hi>viz.</hi> Lead us not into Temptation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That God would ſo ſubdue the Fleſh, over-rule the World, and reſtrain Satan, our Spiritual Enemy, that we and others may not be tempted to Sin, however may not fall into it, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially not live impenitently in it, and that we and others may not provoke God by our Sinning and Impenitence to Puniſh us with Evils and Miſeries, Temporal, Spiritual and Eternal.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is that Form of Praiſe and Thanksgiving which uſually concludes the Lord's Prayer, call'd the Doxology?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For thine is the Kingdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which we Praiſe God aſcribing to him eternal Sovereignty over all, Power to do all, and Glory from all, and from theſe Attributes of God we take encouragement in our Prayers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Senſe of <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the word <hi>Amen,</hi> we declare our Belief that God can, our Hope that he will, and our Deſire that he may grant our Requeſt, or, I truſt that God of his Mercy and Goodneſs will grant what I pray for.</p>
                  <p>Thus in a fit Method and few Words, this Prayer compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends and Summs up all Neceſſaries, as may further appear by this ſhort Paraphraſe of the Learned, Pious and Judicious Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Merciful Lord God, who haſt vouchſafed to adopt and receive us thy unworthy Creatures into the number of thy Children and Heirs of thy Kingdom; We beſeech thee grant us the Aſſiſtance of thy Grace, that we may reverently Worſhip thee, diligently Serve thee, and readily and chearfully Obey thy Holy Will here on Earth, even as thoſe bleſſed Spirits do in Heaven. And whereas by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of our many Weakneſſes and Frailties we are often hindered and always negligent in the Performance of theſe Duties, we beſeech thee continually to reclieve and ſupply us with all Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:103580:9"/> 
                     <hi>Neceſſaries for our help and furtherance in thy Service; And in whatſoever we have hitherto been wanting, or have otherwiſe tranſgreſs'd thy holy Will, we beſeech thee mercifully paſs by and pardon it, even as we our ſelves do heartily and ſincerely forgive all thoſe who have wronged or offended us; And that we may not for the future fall again into the like Sins, we beſeech thee graciouſly to aſſiſt and preſerve us in all Temptations, and Powerfully defend and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from all the Aſſaults of our daily Enemies, the World, the Fleſh and the Devil;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For Thou, O Lord, art the Supreme King; Thou art able to do all things, and to Thee is due the Honour and Glory of all, both in this World and that which is to come.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Doxology left out in ſome Offices?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Since St. <hi>Luke</hi> leaves it out, it is omitted ſome time, when the Office is not matter of Praiſe.</p>
                  <p>If you deſire a further Explanation, it is already excellently performed in this Method, by ſeveral Learned and Reverend Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to which I referr you, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Oxford</hi> Explanation of the Church Catechiſm; Dr. <hi>William</hi>'s Expoſition of the ſame: And once for all, ſo is the Creed, and the Ten Commandments, and the whole Church Catechiſm: And if you have Skill and Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, you will do well in reading the Reverend and Learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s Practical Catechiſm, (a Tract never to be highly enough valued) and the Right Reverend Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> on the Creed, and the Reverend Dr. <hi>Comber,</hi> with many other Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Reſponſes.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY are they ſo called?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the People anſwer the Prieſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Reaſon for this Cuſtom?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In conformity to the Primitive Practice.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Hereby the Conſent of the Congregation is declared to what we pray for, and it is the Unity of Mind and Voice, and this Agreement in Prayer which hath the Promiſe of prevailing.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This grateful Variety and different manner of Addreſs ſerves to quicken the People's Devotion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It engageth their Attention; and ſince they have their ſhare of Duty, they muſt expect till their Turn come, and give heed to do it right, and prepare for their next Reſponſe.</p>
                  <p>Whereas when the Miniſter doth all, the People naturally grow ſleepy and heedleſs, as if wholly unconcern'd; let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore gratefully embrace this Privilege, and make our Reſponſes gravely, and with an audible Voice, which we ſhall find to be a great Help to our Devotion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:103580:10"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do theſe Reſponſes conſiſt of?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The two firſt of Prayers taken out of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms (the great Storehouſe of Primitive Devotion).</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are they placed here?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Firſt <hi>(O Lord, open thou our,</hi> &amp;c.) is fitly placed here, with reſpect to thoſe Sins we lately confeſſed; and if we be fully ſenſible of our guilt, as we ought to be, it will be needful for us to beg ſuch Evidences of our Pardon, as may free us from the Terrors which ſeal up our Lips; and then we ſhall be fit to praiſe God heartily in the Pſalms which follow.</p>
                  <p>The Second <hi>(O God, make ſpeed,</hi> &amp;c.) is the Paraphraſe of that remarkable Supplication, <hi>viz. Hoſannah;</hi> which ſignifies, Save now, Lord, we beſeech thee.—When we look back to thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Evils that have taken hold on us, we cry to God to ſave us ſpeedily from them by his Mercy; and when we look forward to the Duties we are about to do, we pray that he will make haſt to help us by his Grace, without which we cannot do any acceptable Service.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q</hi> What do the other two Reſponſes conſiſt of?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Of Praiſes: Firſt, <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we riſe up at <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Upon Suppoſition that our Pardon is granted, we riſe up with joy to ſing, <hi>Glory be to the,</hi> &amp;c. which is a Paraphraſe upon the Song of the Seraphims, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy;</hi> and gives equal Glory to every Perſon of the Trinity, becauſe each Perſon is <hi>Very God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. We riſe up to ſhew how reſolved we are to ſtand faſt in the Faith of the Holy Trinity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. <hi>Why is it added,</hi> As it was in the Beginning?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew that this was the Primitive Faith, againſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> who had introduced a new Form of Doxology; ſo that now it ſerves for two Uſes: Firſt, as a ſhorter Creed; and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for a Hymn of Praiſe. And to quicken us herein, we declare it was ſo in the Beginning; For the Angels ſung the Praiſes of the Trinity, in the Morning of the Creation, <hi>Job</hi> 38. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the Word <hi>Doxology</hi> ſignifie?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A Song of Praiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Which is the ſecond Reſponſe of Praiſe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. Praiſe the Lord:</hi> Which is no other than the Engliſh of <hi>Hallelujah.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this ſhort Hymn placed here?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As a return to, <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c. For as in that we worſhipped the Trinity; ſo in this we do the Unity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As a triumphant Hymn upon the joyful News of our Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and the overthrow of our ſpiritual Enemies, for which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103580:10"/> ſaith the Prieſt, <hi>Praiſe the Lord:</hi> And the People readily obey him, replying, <hi>The Lord's name be praiſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is a proper Preface to the Pſalms, called in the Hebrew the Book of Praiſes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> XCV Pſalm.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY do we begin with this Pſalm?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is a very proper Preparatory to the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Duties, and is called the Invitatory Pſalm; and contains a threefold Exhortation.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Firſt, To praiſe God; ſhewing the Manner how, externally and internally, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. And the Reaſon why, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4, 5.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Second Exhortation is, to pray to this mighty God for the Manner, humbly giving the Reaſon, <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The third Exhortation is, to hear his Word, directing us to the Manner, ſpeedily, willingly, <hi>v.</hi> 8. and warning us by the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the <hi>Jews</hi> and their Puniſhment, that we may not deſtroy our Souls, by deſpiſing and diſtruſting God's Word as they did.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Pſalms ordered to be read monthly?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In conformity to the ancient Practice.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That they may be made the more familiar to the People, being of all Scripture the fulleſt of Devotion; ſo that without difficulty every Man may apply them to his own Caſe, either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or by way of Accommodation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Pſalms read ſtanding?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By the Erection of our Bodies we expreſs the Elevation or lifting up our Souls to God, and Standing is one of the Poſtures of Supplicants, and the Pſalms do chiefly conſiſt of Prayer and Praiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> That we may be devout in this holy Exerciſe, pray inform us how we may ſort every Pſalm.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Some are of Inſtruction explaining the Creation, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 8. 104, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> or the Providence, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 37. 139, 147. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> or the Paſſion, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 22. 69.) or the Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt, as <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2. 16. 90. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> or his laſt coming to judgment, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 50. 97.)</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Some Pſalms are of Exhortation, ſtirring us up to ſome Acts of moral Vertues; as <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 15. 101.) or Poſitive Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſtudy God's Law, or call on his name, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 1. 34. 119. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> or warning us againſt Sin, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 7. 11. 58. 64. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> eſpecially by Puniſhments inflicted on his own People, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 78. 105. 106 <hi>&amp;c.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Others are Pſalms of Supplication for Pardon, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 25. 51. 143. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> for Peace, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 4. 42. 63.) for Patience, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 10. 23. 39. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> and for Deliverance, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 55. 59. 71.) for others, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 21. 72. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> for the King, for the Church, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 68. 79. 80. <hi>&amp;c.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Others are Pſalms of Praiſe and Thankſgiving for God's Mercies, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 103. 136. 145.) for Health, as <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 116. 130.) for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103580:11"/> Plenty and Wealth, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 65. 144.) Victory over our Enemies, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 18. 149.) for mercy to our Souls, <hi>(Pſ.</hi> 66. 111. 118.)</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Which are thoſe Pſalms that are call'd, <hi>The Seven Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tential Pſalms.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Pſalm the 6. 32. 38. 51. 102. 130. 143.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is <hi>Glory to the Father,</hi> &amp;c. uſed at the end of every Pſalm?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe we do not only glorifie the Holy Trinity, (which Myſtery is more explicitly revealed to us under the Goſpel, than it was under the Law; and by it we ſignifie, that we believe the ſame God was worſhipped by them as by us; the ſame God that is glorified in the Pſalms having been from the beginning <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Holy Ghoſt.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. But we alſo ſix, as it were, this part of the Old Teſtament for the Service of God under the Goſpel, and make them Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Offices.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are two Leſſons read, one out of the Old Teſtament, and another out of the New?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew the Harmony and Agreement of both; what was foretold in the one, is fulfilled in the other.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This Method of Reading doth tend, or fitly ſerve, that from the ſmaller things the Mind may go forward to the Knowledge of greater.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is Holy Scripture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A perfect Revelation of God's Will, as far as is neceſſary to our Salvation; and a compleat Rule both for our Faith and Manners.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are any Chapters omitted to be read?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are ſuch as have been read already, as the <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles</hi> being for the moſt part the ſame with the <hi>Kings,</hi> or elſe full of Genealogies.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The more profitable Chapters are read, the difficulter being not ſo properly ſaid to be omitted, as to be remitted to private Conſideration.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Apocryphal appointed to be read?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not as any Rule of Faith, but becauſe they are excellent Inſtructions of Life and Converſation, and accounted neareſt to Divine of any Writings; and therefore may be read publickly with Profit, and more ſafely than Sermons can be ordinarily preached there.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Books call'd Apocryphal.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is doubted whether they be true Scripture, or not certainly known to be ſo; for ſo the Greek word ſignifies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> That we may profit by hearing the Old Teſtament; pray inform us what the Moral Part of the Law will teach us?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It will teach us what is Sin, together with the Bleſſings and Curſings expreſſed in Phraſes relating to things temporal; but we may ſpiritually apply them.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:103580:11"/>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the Hiſtory of Holy Scripture ſerve for?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To confirm our Faith in God's Providence, and comfort us in Affliction, and to warn us againſt Sin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Directions do the Poetick Books of Holy Scripture give us, <hi>viz.</hi> the Songs, Hymns and Pſalms.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Principally to magnify God's Power and Wiſdom, and to render him thanks for Mercies received and Deliverances wrought, and to act prudently in all Eſtates and Conditions, and furniſh us with excellent Proofs of that great Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is the <hi>wiſeſt thing in the World to be a good Man.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do the Prophecies ſerve for?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To excite us to admire the Foreſight and Truth of God, and teach us to truſt in him for that which is not yet accompliſhed; and particularly they abundantly prove, that <hi>Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and Saviour of the World.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What may we learn by hearing the New Teſtament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In the Goſpels we may ſee God's Love to us, and the great Things which <hi>Jeſus</hi> did and ſuffered for us, whoſe Doctrine is the perfect Rule, and his Practice the compleat Example of all Piety and Vertue; and God hath ſo ſet him that we might fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his Steps.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Out of the Epiſtles we may learn the higher Myſteries of Faith, and the more peculiar duties of our Religion, and the Privileges and Rewards of Chriſtians.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Hymns.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY are the Hymns appointed to be read after the firſt and ſecond Leſſon?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Beſides Antiquity there is great Reaſon for this Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Hymns; for by this variety People are ſecured againſt Wearineſs and Diſtraction: But the chief Reaſon is, in reſpect to the great benefit we receive from the Word of God; for which we do daily praiſe him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are they ſung ſtanding?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Muſick makes the Service of God more eaſie; and Singing enkindles a holy Flame in the Mind and Affections: And by the Poſture of Standing, we fitly expreſs the lifting up of our Hearts in Joy, and it is a Reverend Poſture in our Addreſſes to God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Hymns call'd the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> the <hi>Magnificat,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe theſe are the firſt words in the Hymns in Latin, as <hi>Te Deum Laudamus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Who compoſed the <hi>Te Deum,</hi> and what doth it contain?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> compoſed it, and it contains three Particulars, 1. An Act of Praiſe, a Confeſſion of Faith, and a Supplication.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is not <hi>Glory to the Father,</hi> &amp;c. annex'd to the <hi>Te Deum</hi> as well as to the other Hymns?</head>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103580:12"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Te Deum</hi> is a kind of Creed, expreſs'd in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of a <hi>Glory be to the Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Pray give an account of the other Hymns, appointed to be ſaid after the firſt and ſecond Leſſons.</head>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> Benedicite.</head>
                     <p>THIS Hymn, the Song of the three Children, is ſometimes uſed after the Firſt Leſſon; which although it be not Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Scripture, yet it is an exact Paraphraſe on the 148 Pſalm, and ſo like thereto in Words and Senſe, that whoever deſpiſeth this, reproacheth that part of the ſacred Canon. As for the matter of it, it is an elegant Summons to all God's Works to praiſe him; intimating that they all ſet out his Glory, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite us who have the benefit of them, to praiſe and magnifie his Name for them; or it is as if they had ſaid, the Lord is to be praiſed by or in theſe things; when the Leſſon treats of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation or any wonderful act of God's Providence, then it is very proper to uſe this Hymn.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> Benedictus.</head>
                     <p>THIS Hymn was compoſed by holy <hi>Zachary</hi> upon the firſt notice, that God had ſent a Saviour to Mankind, and is one of the firſt Evangelical Hymns indicted by God's Spirit upon this occaſion, and its fitneſs for this place is unqueſtionable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> C Pſalm.</head>
                     <p>THIS Pſalm was firſt compoſed for a Form of Publick Thankſgiving, to be ſung by courſe at the Oblation of the Peace-Offering; and ſo may well be uſed by us after we have heard the Goſpel of Peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> Magnificat.</head>
                     <p>THIS Hymn was indicted by the Bleſſed Virgin, and when we hear in the Leſſons like Examples of God's Mercy, and are told of thoſe Prophecies and Promiſes which are now fulfill'd in Chriſt's Birth, we may be expected to rejoice with her in the ſame Words.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> XCVIII Pſalm.</head>
                     <p>THERE is a great Similitude between this Pſalm and the <hi>Magnificat,</hi> only the <hi>98th</hi> Pſalm ſeems more proper, when the Evening firſt Leſſon mentions ſome great and eminent Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of God's People.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103580:12"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> Nunc dimittis.</head>
                     <p>AFter the ſecond Evening Leſſon out of the Epiſtles of the Holy Apoſtles, the <hi>Nunc dimittis</hi> is moſt commonly uſed; A Hymn compoſed by <hi>Simeon;</hi> The occaſion of it was his meeting Chriſt in the Temple; and though we cannot ſee our Saviour with our bodily Eyes, as he did, yet he's by the Writings of the Apoſtles daily preſented to the Eyes of our Faith; and if we were as much concern'd for Heaven; and as looſe from the Love of the World, as old <hi>Simeon</hi> was, and as we ought to be; we might upon the View of Chriſt in his holy Word by Faith be daily ready to ſing this Hymn.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of the</hi> LXVII Pſalm.</head>
                     <p>THIS Pſalm is parallel to the former Evangelical Hymn; <hi>David</hi> prayed for that ſaving Health, which old <hi>Simeon</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiced to ſee, and both of them praiſed God upon the Foreſight they had, that it would be made known to us, as it is this day, by the Voices of the Apoſtles.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Apoſtles Creed.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is it called the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Creed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is called a <hi>Creed</hi> from the Latin word <hi>Credo, to believe;</hi> becauſe it contains ſuch Points of Chriſtian Doctrine, as are moſt neceſſary to be believed.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It's called the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> partly becauſe of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Doctrine contained in it; but rather, becauſe it was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Apoſtles, or at leaſt, in or near the Apoſtolical Times; and it conſiſts alſo of Twelve Articles, according to the number of the Twelve Apoſtles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why did the ancient Councils make new ones?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They declare they did (not make new ones) only largely expound ſuch Articles as Hereticks diſputed againſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> If this be a genuine and true Compoſure, then is it not of equal Authority with the holy Scriptures?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 'Tis the ſame thing in a <hi>Compendium</hi> or ſhort Way, and differs only in Form, not in Senſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Creed placed after the Leſſons, and before the Prayers?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We confeſs that Faith which the Leſſons teach.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It's the Foundation of all our Petitions, for we cannot call on him on whom we have not believed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Creed often repeated?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we had need look well to our Faith, and be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103580:13"/> careful to keep that intire; by often rehearſing we guard our Souls with it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It's a plighting our Faith and Fidelity to God; and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is as neceſſary to Salvation, as believing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why muſt we repeat it with an audible Voice?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe by ſo doing every one gives his poſitive and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Aſſent; and by it evidenceth to the Church his ſound Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it repeated ſtanding?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By this Geſture we ſignifie our readineſs to profeſs, and our reſolution to adhere and ſtand to this Faith, and earneſtly contend for it. And in our daily uſe of this Sacred Form, let us devoutly apply every Article to be both a ground for our Prayer, and a guide to our Lives.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we Bow at the Name of <hi>Jeſus?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The mentioning of the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> puts us in Mind of him we owe all manner of Reverence to, which we expreſs by Bowing. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Stillingfleet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we ſay <hi>Amen</hi> after the rehearſing of it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To teſtify our ſtedfaſt belief of it, and our deſire to live as thoſe that heartily believe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by the word <hi>I Believe.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As with a certain and full perſwaſion I aſſent; ſo with a fix'd and undaunted reſolution I profeſs, and with this Faith in my Heart and Confeſſion in my Mouth, in reſpect of the whole Body of the Creed and every Article, I ſincerely, readily and reſolvedly ſay, <hi>I Believe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How may we know when we rightly believe in God the Father?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When we love him, fear him and ſerve him, as our great Creator and merciful Preſerver.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How may we know when we rightly believe in God the Son?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When we ſubmit to him, truſt in him and obey him, as our only Lord and Saviour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How may we know when we rightly believe in God the Holy Ghoſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When we follow his Directions, and make uſe of his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as our Guide, Sanctifier and Comforter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is God the Son ſaid in the Catechiſm to redeem me and all Mankind, when the greateſt part periſh without the benefit of his Redemption?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The price of his Blood which he paid was ſufficient for the Ranſom of the whole World, and is available to as many as God in his abundant Goodneſs and Mercy ſhall judge worthy to be Partakers of the Inheritance with the Saints in Life; but to none of thoſe that do profeſs to be the Diſciples of the Holy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103580:13"/> Jeſus, but ſuch as obſerve the Conditions, <hi>viz.</hi> Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance required in his Bleſſed Goſpel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How is the Holy Ghoſt ſaid to Sanctify all the Elect People of God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By calling them out and ſeparating them from the reſt of the World (which is properly to Sanctify) as well as by putting good Motions and Affections in them, and inſpiring them with Holineſs, by which they become God's choice and peculiar People.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What may we mean when we ſay Chriſt deſcended into Hell?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The word <hi>Hell</hi> is a Saxon word, which is as much as co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered or hidden, and in the Original Propriety both of the Greek and Engliſh, it ſignifies no more than the place which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen, or removed from Men's ſight; ſo that the meaning may be, When all the Sufferings of Chriſt were finiſh'd upon the Croſs, and his Soul ſeparated from his Body, altho' his Body was dead, his Soul dy'd not, but underwent the condition of the Souls of ſuch as die, being he dy'd in the Similitude of a Sinner, his Soul went to the place where the Souls of Men are kept who die for their Sins, and ſo did wholly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the Law of Death, contenting himſelf during his three days of Humiliation with the imperfect Happineſs which the Souls of Holy Men are under till the general Reſurrection from the Dead. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Pearſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Church call'd Holy and Catholick?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is call'd Holy, becauſe it is joined to God in Covenant, and the true Members of it are ſanctified by the Spirit of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And it is call'd Catholick or Univerſal, becauſe it is ſpread over all the World, and not confined as it was among the <hi>Jews</hi> to one particular place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What may we underſtand by the Communion of Saints?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That ſuch Perſons as are truly ſanctified in the Church of Chriſt, have fellowſhip with God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, as dwelling with them, and taking up their Habitations in them; that they partake of the Care and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the bleſſed Angels; that beſide the external fellowſhip which they have in the Word and Sacraments with all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, they have an intimate Union and Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with all the Saints on Earth as living Members of Chriſt, and have fellowſhip likewiſe with all the Saints departed in the true Faith and Fear of God. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Pearſon.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If this Anſwer be too myſtical and obſcure, embrace this pithy and plain one; The Chriſtian Church or Society of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as one Body, is United by a participation of all Spiritual things, as Word, Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Communication of all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103580:14"/> Temporal things, and a fellow-feeling of one anothers condition by all the Members of the Body.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of St.</hi> Athanaſius<hi>'s Creed, commonly ſo called.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT's an Explanation of the great Myſteries of the Trinity, and of Chriſt's Incarnation, againſt the <hi>Arrians</hi> and other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and hath been received with great Veneration by the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches; and many of the Reformed as well as the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> do hold, that <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> was the Author; and all agree that nothing in this or the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed materially different from that which the Apoſtles Creed had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, nor nothing really ſuperadded to it, but were deſigned by the Compilers, to fence the Catholick Orthodox Faith againſt the Corruptions and Depravations; or elſe from the Doubtings and Contradictions of Hereticks, and is the Quinteſſence of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Orthodox Divinity.</p>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Cenſures affix'd in the beginning, middle, and end of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They muſt be interpreted by their Oppoſition to thoſe Hereſies that had invaded the Church, which were Acts of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality in them, that broached and maintained them againſt the Apoſtolick Doctrine, and contradictory to that Foundation which had been reſolved on; and were therefore to be anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matized after this manner, and with Deteſtation baniſhed out of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If any ſcruple at the poſitive denying Salvation to ſuch as do not believe theſe Articles, let them remember ſuch as hold any fundamental Hereſies are condemned in Scripture; and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are called Damnable Hereſies.</p>
                  <p>Let us therefore firmly believe and devoutly uſe this Form, bleſſing God for theſe clear Explications of the ſublime Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Trinity and <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Incarnation; in which we muſt ſtrive to underſtand as much as we can, and ſupply the Reſt with Silence, Submiſſion and Adoration.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Verſicles and Reſponſals, or ſhort Verſes and Anſwers.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY, after we have repeated the Creed, do we begin with the Form of Salutation, <hi>viz. The Lord be with you?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such mutual Salutations are excellent Expreſſions of the Communion of Saints, and Incentives and Provocations to Charity, and Love one of another, ſince we cannot pray with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God's Help, therefore the Miniſter prays, <hi>That the Lord may</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:103580:14"/> 
                     <hi>be with them to aſſiſt them;</hi> and ſince the Miniſter prays for all the People, they deſire he may heartily and devoutly offer up theſe Prayers in their Behalf, ſaying, <hi>The Lord be with thy Spirit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Words <hi>Let us pray,</hi> often repeated?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is a kind of Watch-Word, or Signal of Battel, to ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon us all with united Forces to beſiege Heaven it ſelf with our Holy Importunities: And,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It's a Warning to every one, to lay aſide all vain Thoughts, and only to mind this great Work we have in Hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Verſicles, <hi>Lord have Mercy upon us,</hi> Three times repeated?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is a moſt Pathetick Petition of Mercy to the Bleſſed Trinity, called by the Ancients <hi>a Short Litany,</hi> and is a Preparation to the Lord's Prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Lord's Prayer again repeated?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it conſecrates all the reſt of our Prayers, and makes way for them, and if we did not put up any Petition with Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vency enough before; we may now make amends for it, by ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that with a double Earneſtneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe ſhort Verſicles and Reſponſals uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It was the Primitive Way of Praying, and they contain the Sum of all the following Collects.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Firſt, <hi>O Lord, ſhew thy Mercy,</hi> &amp;c. being a Petition for Mercy and Salvation, anſwers to the <hi>Sunday</hi> Collect.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Second, <hi>O Lord, ſave the King,</hi> anſwers to the Collects for the King and his Family.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Third, <hi>Endue thy Miniſters,</hi> &amp;c. and the Fourth, <hi>O Lord, ſave thy People,</hi> &amp;c. anſwer the Collect for the Clergy and People.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Fifth, <hi>Give Peace in our Time,</hi> &amp;c. anſwers the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Evening Collects, for Peace and Safety.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Sixth, <hi>O God, make clean,</hi> &amp;c. anſwers the Morning and Evening Collects for Grace.</p>
                  <p>And thus by this Alternate Way of Reſponſes, or anſwering and ſpeaking by turns one after another, firſt the Miniſter, then the People, we fit our ſelves the better for the following Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Are there any other Reaſons for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of theſe Verſicles and Reſponſals?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They refreſh the Peoples Attention, and teach them their Part at Publick Prayers, and unite the Affection of them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and help to keep them in a League of perpetual Amity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Prieſt, ſometimes kneel, and ſometimes ſtand?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Miniſter, as a Sinner, kneels with the People in all Confeſſions and Penitential Prayers, but ſtands in other Offices to ſignifie his Office and Authority.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:103580:15"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we turn to the Eaſt in our Prayers and Creed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it's accounted the moſt worthy Part of the World, by being firſt viſited by the riſing Sun; which may mind us of the great Honour and Majeſty of the Perſon we ſpeak to.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Altar, or Holy Table, is placed there, where God affords his moſt Gracious and Myſterious preſence, and the Prieſt or Miniſter uſed to officiate there, and it was look'd upon as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly to turn their Backs upon one or the other in their Prayers or Poſtures.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Time, the whole World wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped toward the Eaſt, and the Chriſtians from the beginning built their Churches and worſhipped themſelves toward the Eaſt, not only in oppoſition to the <hi>Jews</hi> who worſhipped towards the Weſt, but becauſe they expected our Saviour, who is call'd <hi>Oriens ex alto,</hi> or the day-ſpring from on high to come from thence according to his promiſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 27.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Collects.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY are theſe ſhort Forms of Prayer uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe our Saviour himſelf taught and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the frequent uſe of brief Forms of Prayer, and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians were wont to pray in that manner, from whom the Collects were derived.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are they called Collects?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are Collected generally out of the Epiſtles and Goſpels, and are a brief Collection of all things neceſſary for Soul and Body.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Or becauſe they are repeated in Publick, when the People are collected and gathered together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How long have they been uſed in the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Moſt of them are above a Thouſand Years old, having been uſed in the Weſtern Church, from the Time of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, and are Forms for any Bleſſing, or any Grace that we would ask for our ſelves, or others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Pray direct us where we may find among them Prayers on every Occaſion?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> If we would pray for things ſpiritual for our own Souls, <hi>viz.</hi> for the Gifts of the Spirit, See <hi>the Prayer for St.</hi> Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas<hi>'s Day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. If we would pray for Pardon, See the 12, the 21, 24. <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. If for the Benefit of Chriſt's Death and Acceptance through him, See <hi>Annunciation</hi> and <hi>Purification,</hi> and 2. <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phany.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:103580:15"/>
                  <p n="4">4. If for the Comfort, Direction and Illumination of the Spirit, See 1. after <hi>Aſcenſion, Whitſunday,</hi> and 19. after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. If for the Succeſs of our Hearing, Reading and Faſting, See St. <hi>Barth.</hi> St. <hi>Luke,</hi> 2. <hi>Ad.</hi> 1. <hi>Lent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If for Succeſs of our Prayers, 10. and 23. after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. If for Grace in general, to convert us from Sins, See 1. <hi>Adv.</hi> 1. after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> St. <hi>Andrew, James, Matthew.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If to deliver us from Temptation, 4. <hi>Adv.</hi> 4. after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> 18. <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If to enable us to do good, 5. after <hi>Eaſter</hi> 1, 9, 11, 13, 17, 25. after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If to bring us finally to eternal Glory, <hi>Epiph.</hi> 6. after <hi>Epiph.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. If for the particular Graces of Regeneration, See <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas-Day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If for Charity, See <hi>Quinquageſ. Sunday.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If for Mortification, See <hi>Circumciſion, Eaſt. Even.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Contrition, See <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Love of God, See 3. and 4. after <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Heavenly Deſires, See <hi>Aſcenſion-Day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For a Right and Firm Faith, <hi>Trinity-Sunday</hi> 7. after <hi>Trinity,</hi> and St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> St. <hi>Mark.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Grace to imitate Chriſt, 6. <hi>Lent,</hi> 2. after <hi>Eaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For Grace to imitate his Saints, See St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> St. <hi>John Baptiſt, All Saints,</hi> and <hi>Innocents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we would pray for Temporal Bleſſings,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. For God's Providence, See 2, 3, 4, 20. after <hi>Trinity</hi> and St. <hi>Michael.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. For Deliverance from Enemies and Judgments, See the 3. of <hi>Lent, Sexag. Septuageſ.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. For Support under Afflictions, 4. of <hi>Lent.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4. For Defence, 3, 4. after <hi>Epiphany.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>For Supply of all good things, 6. 15. after <hi>Trin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we would pray for Body and Soul both, 2, 5. of <hi>Lent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thoſe without the Church, See <hi>Good-Friday.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thoſe within, that the People may have Truth, Unity, and Peace, 5. after <hi>Epiph. Good-Friday,</hi> St. <hi>John, Simon, Jude,</hi> and the 5, 16, 22. after <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the Miniſters may be fit, diligent and ſucceſsful, See St. <hi>Matthias,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> 3. of <hi>Advent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why in the Collect for Peace, do we pray, That God would <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend us in</hi> (and not from) <hi>the Aſſaults of our Enemies?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the latter is more than ever he promiſed, or we can expect; but in the former we pray, tho they attack us, they may not be able to hurt us.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Difference do you obſerve betwixt the Collect for Peace, in the Morning, and that in the Evening?</head>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103580:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We beg outward Peace in the Morning, to ſecure us againſt the Troubles of the World, in which the Buſineſs of the Day engageth us; and in the Evening we beg inward Peace, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and quiet our Minds when we are to take our Reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What pray we for in theſe Words, <hi>Lighten our Darkneſs?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That our Underſtandings may be enlightned with the Knowledge of God's Providence, and our Hearts cheared with the Aſſurance of his Protection.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If that anſwer be too Allegorical thus, That God by the Light of his Countenance and Favour would protect us in this diſconſolate time of Darkneſs, and chear us with the aſſurance of his Protection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> By whom was the Prayer for the King made, and what doth that Expreſſion mean, <hi>The only Ruler of Princes?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Firſt Reformers of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> made the Prayer, and by that Expreſſion we declare that Kings are only accountable to God; therefore we have the more need to pray for them, that he would direct them to do well, and guide them who are to rule us, that this their mighty Power may be our Safety and our Peace; for if it ſhould be otherwiſe, we neither will nor can oppoſe them, having no other Arms againſt our Prince but Prayers and Tears.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is that Expreſſion in the Prayer for the Clergy uſed, <hi>viz. who alone worketh great Marvels?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe to make a Church, and to beſtow miraculous Gifts on it, to gather it out of Infidels and to protect it from its Enemies, is an Act of as great Power, and a greater Miracle of Love than to create the World, therefore the Preface is very ſuitable.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Who are meant by Curates in the Prayer for the Clergy?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Prieſts and Deacons, to whom the Biſhop commits the Care of Souls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by that word <hi>Expedient,</hi> in the Prayer of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Leſt we have ignorantly asked any thing unfit, we put in this caution, That God will fulfil our Petitions ſo as may be moſt expedient for us, that is, How, When and Which of them he pleaſeth, and ſees will be for our good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Bleſſing pronounced by the Biſhop, if preſent?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For the Honour of his Authority, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 7.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the Bleſſing contain, and in what Poſture ought we to receive it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It contains the whole Order of our Salvation, the Firſt for our Juſtification, the Second for our Conſolation, and the Third for Sanctification, which ought to be received by us
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103580:16"/> on our Knees, for it's God that bleſſeth us by the Mouth of his Miniſter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Litany.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHAT doth the Name ſignifie?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> An humble and earneſt Supplication made to God in Adverſity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> When were theſe Forms firſt brought into the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> About Four Hundred Years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in Times of great Calamity, for the appeaſing of God's Wrath.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Others think the Practice is derived from the Apoſtles and the Cuſtom of their Times.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> By what Motives are your Addreſſes urged?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By Two: Becauſe we are miſerable, and becauſe we are Sinners.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do the People anſwer to every Petition?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By theſe Suffrages their Devotion is excited, quickned and exerciſed, and every Word is ſignificant; for there,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. We declare we ask every thing with Humility and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſs, by the word <hi>We Beſeech.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. With Faith by calling him, we pray unto <hi>Good Lord.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. We declare we ſeek not to Saints or Angels to hear us, but to our God alone, <hi>We beſeech Thee,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>All which ſhews the ſtupidity and baſeneſs of thoſe who are Mute at this part of this excellent Litany, whoſe Bodies are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but their Souls (it is to be feared) are abſent from this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; for whoſoever would perform it with a preſent Mind cannot be better helped by any Means, than by carefully atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, When and How he ought to ſay this Devout Anſwer, <hi>We Beſeech,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Litany broke into ſo many ſhort Ejaculations, and not one continued Prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That the Intention and Devotion, which is moſt neceſſary in Prayer may not be dulled, and vaniſh (as in a long Prayer it's apt to do) but be quickned, and the nearer to the End the ſhorter and livelier are the Expreſſions; ſtrengthning our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, by raiſing in us an Apprehenſion of our Miſery and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, and therefore crying out, <hi>O Lamb of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q</hi> Why is the Litany ordered to be read on <hi>Sunday, Wedneſday,</hi> and <hi>Friday?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Upon <hi>Sunday</hi> in Honour to that Day, it being the Chief Service, and on <hi>Wedneſdays</hi> and <hi>Fridays</hi> becauſe they are Days of publick Aſſemblies and Faſtings, and commanded more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to be ſaid by the Miniſter thoſe Days weekly, tho' they be not Holy-days. <hi>Canon the 15<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:103580:17"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we repeat the Firſt Four Verſes intirely after the Miniſter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is as well a Confeſſion of Faith as an Epitome or Sum of the whole Litany.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we pray to every Perſon in the Holy Trinity, apart?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe as we acknowledge every Perſon by himſelf to be God and Lord, ſo we worſhip each Perſon apart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by a Perſon in the Holy Trinity?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Perſon, is a diſtinct Subſiſtence of the whole Godhead. There are Three Divine Perſons, which are not Three ſeveral Subſtances; but Three diſtinct Subſiſtences, or Three divers Manner of Being of one and the ſame Subſtance and Divine Eſſence, which Divine Eſſence is neither divided nor diſtinguiſh'd; But the Three Perſons in the Divine Eſſence are diſtinguiſh'd among themſelves by their Names, by their Order, and by their Actions or Properties.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Divine Eſſence ſometimes call'd <hi>Unity</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Divine Eſſence common to all the Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons is but One, we call the ſame <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> But becauſe there be Three diſtinct Perſons in this one indiviſible Eſſence, we call the ſame <hi>Trinity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Third Perſon named the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe He is Spiritual without a Body.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe He is Spired, and as it were breathed from both the Father and the Son, that is Proceeding from them both.</p>
                  <p>And He is call'd <hi>Holy,</hi> both becauſe He is Holy in his own Nature, and alſo the immediate Sanctifier of all true Believers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Second Perſon called <hi>God the Son,</hi> and not the Son of God?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Oppoſition to the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie, who denied the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of the Son, therefore we own him to be God equal with the Father, and give him the ſame Worſhip.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Sith no Church in the World hath ſo compleat a Form, pray inſtruct us in that curious and comprehenſive Method?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It's introduced with an Invocation of the Bleſſed Trinity, ſeverally and conjunctly in the Four firſt Verſes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It contains Deprecations for Forbearance, <hi>v.</hi> 5. For Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from Spiritual, Temporal, and Eternal Evils, <hi>v,</hi> 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Noting alſo the Means by which, <hi>v.</hi> 11, 12. and the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Time when, we ſhould be delivered, <hi>v.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It contains Interceſſions for the whole Church, <hi>v.</hi> 14. For this Church, and in it for the King and His Royal Family, <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16, 17, 18. And for the Clergy, <hi>v.</hi> 19. For the Nobility and Magiſtrates, <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21. and the People, <hi>v.</hi> 22. For all Eſtates
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103580:17"/> of Men we beg Peace, <hi>v.</hi> 23. and Grace, <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25, 26, 27. For the Comfort of the Afflicted, <hi>v.</hi> 28, 29, 30, 31. and for Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Enemies, <hi>v.</hi> 32; and we pray for our ſelves, that we may have Plenty, <hi>v.</hi> 33. and Grace, <hi>v.</hi> 34.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It contains Supplications, 1. To preſs the former Petitions in Addreſſes to the Son of God and the whole <hi>Trinity;</hi> and to prevent, or remove evil in the Lord's Prayer, in the Prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Perſecution and the Alternate Requeſts, and to ſanctifie evil not removed in the laſt Collect.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we begin to ask with theſe Deprecations?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Deliverance from Evil is the Firſt Step to Felicity, and the proper Buſineſs of Litany.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. <hi>Why in the Petition for Forbearance do we pray,</hi> That God would not remember the Sins of our Fathers?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When God puniſheth Sin, he's ſaid to remember them, and we know there is a vaſt Heap of our own and our Fathers Sins unrevenged, and God may juſtly puniſh us for them, when we make them ours by Imitation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Sum of all theſe Deprecations?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Deliverance from the Evils of Sin and Puniſhment, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in thoſe two general Words, Evil and Miſchief, which ſignifie Wickedneſs and Miſery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why in the Firſt Place, do we pray to be delivered from the Evil of Sin?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is the Firſt, greateſt, and only real Evil, and the ſole Cauſe of all the Miſchiefs that do befall us; and by it the Church teacheth us, that they begin at the wrong End that pray againſt Affliction rather than Sin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the occaſion of drawing us into this evil?</head>
                  <p>A. The Grafts and Aſſaults of the Devil.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are thoſe Sins mentioned, which concern our ſelves?</head>
                  <p>A. Blindneſs of Heart, Pride, Vain-Glory and Hypocriſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are thoſe Sins againſt our Neighbours?</head>
                  <p>A. Envy, Hatred, Malice, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitableneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. <hi>What mean we by</hi> Fornication and all other deadly Sins?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Fornication is not to be reſtrained to the defiling of ſingle Perſons, but comprehends all Acts of Uncleanneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is any Sin Venial or Pardonable in its own Nature?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: But yet with St. <hi>John</hi> we affirm as to the Event, there is a Sin unto Death, and there is a Sin not unto Death, and it's from thoſe open and grievous Sins of Preſumption which keep Men from Repentance, and uſually end in Damnation; which we pray to be delivered from under the Name of Deadly Sins, of which we have a Catalogue, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9, 10.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do the Deceits of the World, Fleſh and Devil comprehend?</head>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:103580:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All other Kinds of Sin; and becauſe all Sin is managed by thoſe Three Enemies, therefore they are mentioned.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we pray againſt in that Petition, <hi>from Lightning and Tempeſt,</hi> &amp;c?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For the Removal of the Effects, <hi>viz.</hi> Judgments.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What mean we by <hi>Sudden Death?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Either an untimely Death before the Term which Nature allots; or, a violent Death by ſtabbing, burning, drowning, <hi>&amp; o.</hi> or elſe it ſignifies the dying in a Moment of Time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are all theſe kind of Deaths to be prayed againſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they leave our Relations without Comfort.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They leave our worldly Concerns unſettled.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They deprive us of the neceſſary preparative Ordinances for Death.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They give us no Time to fit our Souls for our great Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
                  <p>The Frequency and fearfulneſs of Earthquakes gave the Firſt occaſion to this Prayer againſt Sudden Death (as Dr. <hi>Hakewell</hi> tells us) but tho' this ſort of Calamity be more rare in this than in ſome other Countries, and leſs dreadful now than in former Ages, ſo that this Petition (at leaſt as to us may ſeem leſs need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful upon that account; yet how many are the Caſualties and Dangers we are continually expoſed to, that may put a ſudden Period to our Lives? which to beg the Divine Protection to be preſerv'd and delivered from, a Judicious Author looks upon as the moſt proper and direct ſenſe of this Petition, and let that Man alone (ſaith he) who judgeth this unſit, condemn and reject this Petition againſt Sudden Death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What's comprehended in that Petition, <hi>from Sedition,</hi> &amp;c?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> We pray againſt the Cauſes of thoſe ſad Effects, which ſuch Evils may bring upon the Kingdom and Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why was <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> added ſince King <hi>Charles II</hi>'s Happy Reſtauration?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> did murder one of the beſt of Kings, and Thouſands of his loyal Subjects, and alſo pull'd the Church to pieces.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are the means we pray to be delivered by?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> His <hi>Holy Incarnation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are ſuch Petitions as theſe called by the Latins <hi>Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crationes?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we urge the party, of whom we ask, by all that is dear to him; and in theſe we commemorate all that our dear Redeemer did for us in his Life, at his Death, and after his Death; and by all the Love he ſhewed to us, by all the Torments he endured for us, by all the glorious
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103580:18"/> Things he intends for us; we beſeech him to deliver us from theſe Evils.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is not this called <hi>Conjuration?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes: Ignorant Malice hath ſo cenſured it, when it is the moſt devout and moving Oratory in the World.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the <hi>Croſs</hi> here put for?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not for the Wood, (which the Papiſts ſuperſtitiouſly adore, but) for the Torments he ſuffered thereon; and his <hi>Croſs</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the pains of his Body, his Paſſion, and the Anguiſh of his Mind.</p>
                  <p>All theſe Arguments, devoutly urged, have a mighty Force in them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> When is the ſeaſon that we pray for Deliverance?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is expreſſed in that Petition, <hi>In all Time of our Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is that part which we call <hi>Interceſſion</hi> uſed in the Litany?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is commanded by God, and in Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we ought to deſire Bleſſings for all ſorts of Men?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we begin in our Interceſſions with the Holy Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we ought to be more concern'd for the good of the Whole, than of any particular Part.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we beg of God to Rule and Govern <hi>All Churches</hi> in the right Way, which is left out by the <hi>Romaniſts?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe when theſe Petitions were firſt made, it is not likely that the Doctrine of Infallibility was maintain'd, either in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, or any other Part of the Chriſtian World; and that any particular Church may fall into wrong Ways, the very <hi>Roman</hi> Church which boaſts of its Infallibility has demonſtrated, and by ſad Experience, we find that no particular Church is free from the poſſibility of being deceived, altho' we believe that God will not ſuffer the whole Univerſal Church at once to fall into any grievous Error.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we pray for in thoſe Petitions for the King?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our firſt Requeſts are for the King's ſpiritual Good, that he may be throughly and ſincerely pious from inward Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which will never fail; if he be of the right Faith, then the Prayer is for his Confirmation in it; and if he be perverted, it's a Prayer for his Converſion?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We pray likewiſe that he may be ſupplied with all Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bleſſings, and kept from all kinds of Evil. And if any be ſo wicked as to rebel upon any Pretence whatſoever, Religion, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Property, or the like; we muſt wiſh the Victory may fall always on the King's ſide.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:103580:19"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Prayer for the <hi>Clergy</hi> placed next to that for the <hi>Royal Family?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> both reckoned their Chief Prieſts to be next in dignity to their Kings, and ſo did our pious Anceſtors account them (next to the King) the moſt conſiderable Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Catholick Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Clergy diſtinguiſh'd here into thoſe three Orders, <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts and Deacons?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> All ancient Offices do particularly pray for the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſo diſtinguiſhed, which have from the Beginning been ever in the Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Subſtance of the Prayer?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Prayer we make for them, is the ſame which <hi>Moſes</hi> made for <hi>Levi,</hi> Deut. 33. 8. <hi>Let thy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim and thy Thummim be with thy holy One:</hi> That is, Illumination, or Enlightning, and Perfection, which is excellently Paraphras'd in this Prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are thoſe three Words in the <hi>Litany,</hi> which comprehend all the Miſeries that concern our Bodies?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Danger, Neceſſity, and Tribulation.</p>
                  <p>All Evils are either future and feared, and theſe are implied in the Word <hi>Danger;</hi> or elſe they are preſent, and then they proceed from want of ſome good thing expreſſed by <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> or from ſuffering ſome evil thing ſignified by <hi>Tribulation;</hi> and each of theſe hath its proper Verb ſuted to it, <hi>viz. Succour, Help,</hi> and <hi>Comfort.</hi> So that in this one general Requeſt, we compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend our ſelves and all other afflicted Perſons in the whole World.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> There are ſome who condemn all Antiquity together with our Church, as if They and We pray'd for Thieves and Pirates, becauſe the word is general for <hi>All that Travel,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is a malicious Comment on an innocent Text, for He is properly a Traveller who goes about his allowable or ordinary Occaſions, and it is evident that no other are here meant, but Juſt and Honeſt Men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why after ſo many excellent Petitions preſented to our Heavenly Father, do we make our Addreſſes to our Mediatour, <hi>viz. Son of God, Lamb of God.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That he may recommend us and our Prayers at the Throne of Grace; beſeeching him by his Divinity, and by his Sufferings for us, to accept of our Petitions, and to pardon our Sins; and again, as he's our anointed Mediatour, that he would procure a gracious Anſwer to them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Verſicles added: <hi>Lord have Mercy,</hi> &amp;c?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That our Concluſion may be ſuitable to our Beginning, we cloſe up all with an Addreſs to the whole Trinity for that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103580:19"/> Mercy which we have been begging in ſo many particulars, and this one Word <hi>Mercy</hi> comprehends them all; ſo that this is the Epitome of the whole <hi>Litany.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> When was this laſt part of the <hi>Litany,</hi> called the <hi>Supplications,</hi> firſt collected and put into this Form?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> When the barbarous Nations began to over-run the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, about 600 years after Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Lord's Prayer again repeated?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew the high eſteem that pious Antiquity had of it, and their mean Opinion of their own Inventions and Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, which receive Life and Value from this Divine Form.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe words <hi>(Let us pray)</hi> here uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That the People may not think the Duty is ended, as ſoon as the Reſponſes or Anſwers ceaſe; but are admoniſhed in their Heart (not with their Voice) to join with the Prieſt ſtill.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is not the Prayer againſt Perſecution concluded with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew that the ſame Requeſt is continued in another Form, and what the Prieſt begg'd alone there, all the People join with him to ask in theſe alternate Supplications, or Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in turn.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is not the repeating that Petition twice <hi>(O Lord, ariſe,</hi> &amp;c.) a vain Repetition?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: But a Teſtimony that we are convinced we did wiſely and well, to ask of God now to <hi>ariſe and help us;</hi> that ſo the honour he hath gotten by the wonders of his Mercy may be renewed and confirmed, by this new Act of his Power and Goodneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Doxology placed here?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In imitation of Holy <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 6. 8. and <hi>Pſ.</hi> 22. 25. we having ſuch a God to pray to, in the midſt of our mournful Supplications, do both praiſe God for his ancient Mercies; and alſo in aſſurance we ſhall obtain his Help, praiſe him for his Help beforehand: And as he was glorified for paſt Mercies in the Beginning; ſo he is for the preſent, and ſhall be hereafter for future Bleſſings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we not riſe up when the Doxology is repeated in the <hi>Litany?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe as it's here uſed, and other parts of the <hi>Litany,</hi> before and after, are matters of humble Supplications; and ſo moſt fit to be tendred to God in that Poſture.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We are to conſider, that this Doxology was inſerted when the Litany was (what it is now, but called) Proceſſion; and then it was no Exception, for then Men were ſtanding or walking.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is chiefly meant by that Phraſe: <hi>Mercifully look upon our Infirmities?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103580:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Calamities which Divine Providence hath laid upon us, and which we have juſtly and righteouſly deſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe is there for the occaſional Prayers in general, if the various Miſeries of Mankind are exactly enumerated in the <hi>Litany?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our Miſeries are but barely mentioned there, and at ſome times ſome particular Evils lie ſo heavy upon us; and ſome great mercies are ſo neceſſary for us, that it is requiſite we ſhould have ſolemn Forms upon ſuch Occaſions; that it may fully ſute all our Neceſſities.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. <hi>Why are the</hi> 4. Sundays <hi>before</hi> Chriſtmas <hi>called</hi> Advent Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are to prepare us for Chriſt's <hi>Advent,</hi> or coming in the fleſh, which we call <hi>Chriſtmas.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we commemorate the bleſſed Birth of our Saviour upon the <hi>25th</hi> of <hi>December?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it was the cuſtom of the ancient Church ſo to do, and we have good Reaſon to believe that Chriſt was Born on that Day. <hi>Vide</hi> Dr. <hi>Hammond.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Feaſt of <hi>Circumciſion</hi> obſerved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As by Chriſt's Birth we received the Adoption of Sons, ſo by his Circumciſion the Redemption from the Law.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What do we celebrate upon <hi>Epiphany?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Three glorious Manifeſtations, <hi>viz.</hi> The Star, which was the Gentiles guide to Chriſt; and that of the Trinity at the Baptiſm of Chriſt, in the opening of the Heavens, and of his Divinity by the Miracle of turning Water into Wine, which is thought to have been done on the ſame Day.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Lent.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is a <hi>Sunday</hi> before <hi>Lent</hi> called <hi>Septuageſima?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw. A conſequentia numerandi;</hi> viz. Becauſe the Firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent</hi> is called <hi>Quadrageſima,</hi> containing about forty days from <hi>Eaſter;</hi> therefore the <hi>Sunday</hi> before that, being ſtill further from <hi>Eaſter,</hi> is called <hi>Quinquageſima,</hi> five being the next number above four; and ſo the <hi>Sunday</hi> before that is called <hi>Sexageſima;</hi> and the <hi>Sunday</hi> before that <hi>Septuageſima;</hi> which are all Preparatives to the <hi>Lenten Faſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. It is a Latin word, and ſignifies as much as <hi>Seventy,</hi> and is put for 70 days which end the <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and the next <hi>Sunday</hi> is call'd <hi>Sexageſima,</hi> as containing 60 days, which end on <hi>Thurſday</hi> in <hi>Eaſter</hi> Week; and <hi>Quinquageſima</hi> as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining 50 days before <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and are all Preparatives to the <hi>Lenten Faſt,</hi> which is call'd <hi>Quadrageſima,</hi> containing about 40 days before <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it called <hi>Lent?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:103580:20"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> From the time of the year, the word ſignifies <hi>Spring</hi> in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Language, and is the <hi>Spring-Faſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are forty days obſerved, and at this ſeaſon?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Imitation of our Saviour, who faſted 40 days in the Wilderneſs as <hi>Moſes</hi> did in the Mount, and wherein we might be put in Mind of the ſore Trial and Temptation which Chriſt then endured for our ſakes, whoſe Sufferings ended at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and to prepare us for the holy Communion, which our Church commands to be then Received.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. There's great uſe of this yearly Faſt beſides, <hi>viz.</hi> That the defects of our Weekly Humiliations and Devotions may be thereby ſupply'd; That there may be a Publick Humiliation for Publick Errors (if not for Private Sins) in particular; That the Godly Diſcipline which was anciently in Uſe at this Seaſon, for putting Perſons to open Pennance as ſtood convicted of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Sins, is now laid aſide and neglected. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Patrick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we begin this Faſt on <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſupply the <hi>Sundays</hi> in <hi>Lent</hi> (upon which it was not the Church's Cuſtom to Faſt) and by deducting ſix <hi>Sundays,</hi> and adding theſe four days, the juſt number of forty is made up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday</hi> ſo called?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe anciently Aſhes were ſprinkled upon their heads, to mind them of their Mortality, and what they had deſerved, <hi>viz.</hi> to be burnt to Aſhes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Ember-Weeks.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHat is the Original of thoſe four Weeks of Faſting, now called <hi>Ember-Weeks?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt Chriſtian Biſhops in imitation of the Apoſtles uſed to appoint Faſting and Prayer, when they conferred holy Orders; as ſoon as the Church was ſetled, the Ordination of Miniſters became fixed, and are ſtill obſerved in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for a Preparation to the Ordination of Miniſters.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What other Reaſons may be given for the Obſervation of <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-Faſt?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. Becauſe theſe times are as the Firſt fruits of every Seaſon, which we rightly dedicate to the Service and Honour of God.</p>
                  <p>3 <hi>R.</hi> That beginning theſe ſeveral parts of the year in a holy and ſober Life, we might the better learn how to ſpend the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of every Seaſon.</p>
                  <p>4 <hi>R.</hi> That we may obtain the continuance of God's Favour for the Fruits of the Earth, which at theſe times are for the moſt part ſown, or ſprung up, or ripening or gathered into the Barn.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:103580:21"/>
                  <p>5 <hi>R.</hi> That we might repent us of all our Sins which all the Seaſon before we have committed.</p>
                  <p>6 <hi>R.</hi> That our Bodies might be freed from thoſe Contagious Diſtempers which uſually theſe 4 Seaſons, through the Predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant Humours then reigning do bring along with them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> At what ſeaſon of the year are theſe Faſts obſerved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt is the <hi>Wedneſday, Friday</hi> and <hi>Saturday</hi> after the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> in <hi>Lent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond, after <hi>Whitſunday.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Third, the <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> &amp;c. after <hi>Septemb.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>The Fourth, the <hi>Wedneſday, Friday</hi> and <hi>Saturday</hi> after the <hi>13th.</hi> of <hi>December.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are they call'd <hi>Ember Weeks?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Ancients on thoſe days would eat no Bread, but Cakes made under Embers.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe the old <hi>Saxon</hi> word from which <hi>Ember</hi> is derived, ſignifies to abſtain or forbear Eating.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The true word (in the Judgment of Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> and Sir <hi>Henry Spelman)</hi> is <hi>Imber,</hi> from the old <hi>Saxon</hi> word <hi>Imbren,</hi> i. e. a Circle, and theſe four Faſts keep their certain turns ſo many times in the year, as in a Circle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Reaſon may be given why the Ordination of Miniſters is affixed to theſe ſet times?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That as all Mens Souls are concerned in the ordaining a fit Clergy, all may join in Faſting and Prayer for a Bleſſing on it; and that Biſhops and Candidates, knowing the time, may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare themſelves for this great Work; that no Vacancy may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main long unſupplied; and that the People, if they pleaſe, may be preſent, either to approve or object againſt any, whom they know to be unworthy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the <hi>Sunday</hi> before <hi>Eaſter</hi> call'd <hi>Palm-Sunday?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe as Chriſt came from <hi>Bethany</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they cut down Palm-Branches, and ſtrew'd them in the Way.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the day before <hi>Good-Friday</hi> called <hi>Maunday-Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Chriſt waſhed his Diſciples Feet, and <hi>commanded</hi> them to do ſo likewiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is <hi>Good-Friday</hi> obſerved as a Faſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe on that day our Saviour ſuffered.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are ſome days called <hi>Holy Days?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are taken out of the Common Days and ſet apart to God's Service and Worſhip; either by God's own Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, or the Churches Dedication, in Commemoration of ſome eminent Mercy?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are theſe Days commanded to be obſerved?</head>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:103580:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe (as learned Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> obſerves) they expreſs the Splendor and outward Dignity of our Religion, and are forcible Witneſſes of ancient Truth; are likewiſe Provocations to the Exerciſe of all Piety, and ſhadows of our endleſs Felicity in Heaven, and everlaſting Records on Earth, teaching by the Eye in a manner whatſoever we believe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Feaſt, called <hi>Eaſter,</hi> obſerved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To commemorate the Reſurrection of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, who roſe on the firſt day of the Week, and it is called <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and by the old Saxons <hi>Oſter,</hi> which ſignifies to riſe, from whence we frequently ſay to one on the Ground, <hi>Oaſt up,</hi> when we would have him to riſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. <hi>Why is the</hi> Sunday <hi>following</hi> Eaſter <hi>called</hi> Low-Sunday, <hi>and</hi> Dominica in Albis?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It was the Cuſtom of our Forefathers to obſerve the <hi>Octave</hi> of their high and principal Feaſts; and this is the <hi>Octave</hi> or eighth day after <hi>Eaſter;</hi> upon every <hi>Octave</hi> they uſed to repeat ſome part of that Service which was performed upon the Feaſt itſelf; which is the Reaſon why it's called <hi>Low-Sunday:</hi> The <hi>Sunday</hi> before is <hi>High Eaſter;</hi> and this is a Lower Feaſt, <hi>Low Eaſter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> (as alſo <hi>Whitſunday)</hi> being the ſtated time for Baptiſm in the ancient Church, thoſe who were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd, put on white Garments in token of that pure and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent courſe of life they had now engaged in; this white Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they wore till the next <hi>Sunday</hi> after, and then laid it aſide, whence the <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Eaſter</hi> came to be ſtiled <hi>Dominica</hi> in <hi>Albis,</hi> the <hi>Sunday in White,</hi> it being then that the new Baptiz'd put off their white Garments. <hi>Dr.</hi> Cave.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is <hi>Rogation-Sunday</hi> ſo called?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe upon the three following days, Rogations or Prayers, and Litanies were uſed for a Bleſſing on the Fruits of the Earth that were tender.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To prepare us for our Lord's Aſcenſion Day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is Aſcenſion Day obſerved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It's an Anniverſary Commemoration of Chriſt's Aſcent to Heaven, which gives us hopes of Heaven; in that our Fleſh in the firſt Fruits is thither aſcended.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is <hi>Whitſunday</hi> ſo called?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> From the glorious Light of Heaven, which was then ſent down upon the Earth from the Father of Lights on the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; ſo many Tongues, ſo many Lights.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe the new-baptized (that being a ſolemn time of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm;) call'd of old the <hi>enlightned,</hi> were then cloathed in white Carments call'd <hi>Chryſoms,</hi> as types of ſpiritual Purity and Joy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:103580:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this day called <hi>Pentecoſt?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> ſignifies fifty in <hi>Greek,</hi> and from the <hi>Sunday</hi> after <hi>Good-Friday,</hi> this is the 50th day; ſo the <hi>Jews</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is <hi>Trinity Sunday</hi> ſo called?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Church thought meet, that ſuch a Myſtery as the bleſſed Trinity ſhould be the chief Subject of one day, and this to be the day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What may be the Reaſon that God did not ſo plainly deliver this Myſtery to the <hi>Jews?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Leaſt they ſhould have miſtaken it for a Doctrine of a Plurality of Gods; yet ſome Seeds of that Perfection of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity were diſperſed, and for that Cauſe the Choire of Angels ſing thrice <hi>Holy,</hi> but once <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Converſion of St. <hi>Paul</hi> celebrated, and not his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom; or day of his Death, as other Saints are.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For example ſake, that no Sinner may deſpair.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. For the Joy the Church had at his Converſion, and for the Miracles then wrought.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Purification of the bleſſed Virgin obſerved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Partly in memory of her Purification according to the Law, but chiefly in memory of our Lord's Preſentation in the Temple.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Purification of St. <hi>Mary</hi> called <hi>Candlemas.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe in ancient Times they went in Proceſſion two by two, carrying Candles, and many Lights were ſet up in Churches.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Feaſt of St. <hi>Michael</hi> obſerved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Church holds a Feaſt on that day, in memory of the Holy Angels, becauſe they miniſter to us on Earth, and fight againſt the Devil for us by their Prayers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy is the day, called <hi>All Saints,</hi> obſerved?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we cannot particularly commemorate every Saint, and in thoſe particular Feaſts, which we do celebrate, we may omit ſome of our duty, therefore this day in general is obſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy do we keep the days of the Saints Death, rather than their Birth?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe then they are born Citizens of Heaven.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Then they perfectly triumph over all their Enemies, by which the Church <hi>Militant</hi> is encouraged to perſevere.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy have ſome Holydays Faſts before them, and why have ſome other none?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It was the Religious Cuſtom of the Primitive Times, to ſpend a great part of the Night before the Holidays in Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Prayers, to prepare them for the more ſolemn Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of thoſe Feaſts; and to ſignifie, that we ſhould be, as
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:103580:22"/> the bleſſed Saints were, after a little time of Mortification and Affliction tranſlated into Glory and Joy; but in time, as Charity and Devotion grew cold through Sloth and Reſtineſs, this more troubleſome part of Devotion, the nightly Watches (now called <hi>Vigils)</hi> were laid aſide, and the Faſts only remained.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Sometime the Signification or Myſtery of the Vigil or Faſt ceaſed, then the Vigil or Faſt is omitted; as for Example, St. <hi>Michael</hi> hath no Faſt, becauſe the Angels did not by Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and Mortifications enter into their Joy; but were created in the Joy they have: And ſometime when the Signification holds good, others have no Faſts, becauſe either they fall betwixt <hi>Eaſter</hi> and <hi>VVhitſunday,</hi> or betwixt <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> and <hi>Epiphany,</hi> which the Church holds for ſuch times of Joy and Feſtivity, that they would not have one day among them ſullied by pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Sorrow and Faſting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Office of Baptiſm.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is the Place where the Office of Baptiſm is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, called the <hi>Font?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Rites of Baptiſm in the firſt Times were performed in Fountains and Rivers, becauſe the Converts were many, and thoſe Ages were unprovided of other Baptiſteries, or Baptizing places; and hence it is we call our Baptiſteries, <hi>Fonts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why was Water choſen by Chriſt in this Sacrament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſignifie his Waſhing our Souls from Sin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Form of Baptiſm, as to the Eſſential part of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing?</head>
                  <p>A. In the name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Who inſtituted this Form?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Who are the Subjects of this Baptiſm?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Infants and Perſons grown up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are Infants to be brought to Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That there may be many Witneſſes of this ſolemn Act, and that others may be put in mind of their Vow; and becauſe thus they are admitted Members of our Religious Aſſemblies in the proper place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>VVhat is the meaning of the word <hi>Baptize?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It comes from a Greek word which ſignifies to Waſh, and is apply'd to this Sacrament of Baptiſm, becauſe that is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Waſhing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why muſt Parents and Friends be ſo careful to get their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren baptized?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe by this Ordinance their Original Sin is waſh'd away, and they grafted into the Body of Chriſt; ſo that if they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103580:23"/> die before they have committed actual Sin, they are undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſaved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat if it be neglected by the Fault of the Parents?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They muſt anſwer for putting their Childrens Salvation on ſo great a Hazard; but it is the contempt, and not bare want of the Sacrament, which makes it damnable, and ſo cannot be imputable or prejudicial to the Child.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVho muſt anſwer for them of riper years?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They themſelves muſt make the Covenant with their own Mouths, and the Godfathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are only Witneſſes to the Fact, and muſt be Monitors to them, to live according to their Vow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy doth the Prieſt ask if the Child have been already bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith there is but one Baptiſm, and as we are born but once; ſo we are born again but once.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is not that Baptiſm commanded in the Holy Goſpel to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood only of the Inward and Spiritual Baptiſm, not with <hi>Water,</hi> but the <hi>Holy Ghoſt?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No, by no means; becauſe Acts of inward Faith are, and ought to be often repeated; therefore Baptiſm which cannot be repeated, cannot be the inward but the outward Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>To Baptize with the Holy Ghoſt is peculiar to Chriſt alone, for none can Baptize with the Holy Ghoſt but he who can ſend and beſtow the Holy Ghoſt, which is Blaſphemy to aſcribe to any Creature.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy are Godfathers or Sureties injoined?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Cuſtom gives ſecurity to the Church, that the Child ſhall not be an Apoſtate, and provides a Monitor both for the Child and its Parents, to mind them of this Vow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy do the Godfathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> promiſe in behalf of the Child?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Baptiſm we are making a Covenant. God hath given the Promiſes, which are his Word; and therefore good Reaſon we ſhould give our Word, for the performance of the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on our part: And ſince that Infants cannot make a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant themſelves, the Church lends them the Feet of others to bring them, and the Tongues of others to promiſe for them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Doth the Godfather's Promiſe oblige the Child?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes: For by the wiſeſt Law in the World, Guardians may contract for Minors or Pupils, who are bound to perform what their Guardians have undertaken.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Reaſon may be given why Chriſt appointed this Form?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Since the Belief of the Trinity is the peculiar and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Article of the Chriſtian Religion, therefore Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>points they ſhall be made Chriſtians, by being thus baptized in the name of the three Perſons of the Trinity.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:103580:23"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. This ſolemn naming of three Perſons, is a kind of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to witneſs from Heaven, that we may as it were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs before theſe three Witneſſes our unfeigned Faith, and ſo we have the ſame for Witneſſes of our Faith who make us the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of Salvation, and ſure we ſhall never dare fall off, who have ſeal'd our Profeſſion in the preſence of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is meant by being Baptized in the Name of the three Perſons in the Trinity.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That the Miniſter doth this in God's Name, and by his Power and Commiſſion, and that the Baptized Perſon is dedicated to, and engaged to Worſhip and Serve the Holy Trinity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Prieſt Sprinkle and not Dip?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Efficacy of the Sacrament depends not on the Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Water, but on the Grace of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Coldneſs of our Climate hath made this Cuſtom al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt neceſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Child ſign'd with the Sign of the Croſs on the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For the clearer Manifeſtation, that this Child now belongs to Chriſt, the Church ſets his Sign and peculiar Mark upon it; a Cuſtom by which the Primitive Chriſtians declared their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And it's ſigned in the Forehead, becauſe that this is the feat of Bluſhing and Shame, that we may not be aſhamed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Ought not the Prieſt, and all the People heartily to ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> when the Myſtery is ended?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes, to ſhew they believe the Child to be rightly Baptiz'd, and to deſire God may ratify that in Heaven which is done upon Earth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Effect of Baptiſm?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Salvation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Confirmation.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is Confirmation appointed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> To confirm and ratifie with our own Mouths the Promiſe made by our Godfathers, and to receive new Strength by the Bleſſings and Prayers of the Biſhop.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Is Confirmation a Sacrament, and appointed by Chriſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: But a Holy Rite which the Church obſerves in Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Apoſtles Practice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why had not this Rite a Poſitive Inſtitution by our Lord Jeſus?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Holy Ghoſt (which is herein to be communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated) was not given till after Chriſt's Aſcenſion, <hi>John</hi> 7. 39. yet in his promiſing the Holy Spirit to his Diſciples, and to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:103580:24"/> Remain with his Church for ever, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. 16. he ſeem'd to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that there ſhould be ſome Rite inſtituted by them for the perpetual Collation, or beſtowing of the Spirit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> When did this Office of Confirmation begin?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt Converts whom the Apoſtles Baptized, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm'd by the immediate Hand of God, and He by his Miraculous Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, ſealed their Baptiſm, and atteſted the Religion into which they had entred. But it was not long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles were appointed to miniſter in giving the Holy Spirit to the newly Baptized, and then they inſtituted the Rite of laying on of Hands, and God was pleaſed ſo far to approve their Inſtitution, that he did actually give wonderful Meaſures of the Spirit to thoſe on whom they laid their Hands, thereby honouring the Governours of his Church, and engaging all the Members thereof to be Subject to them, and to be at Peace one with another.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How prove you this out of the Holy Scripture?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> From that famous inſtance <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 14, 15, 16. When the <hi>Samaritans</hi> had been converted and baptized by <hi>Philip</hi> the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con; they did not receive the Holy Ghoſt until St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> had confirm'd them, from whence the Fathers generally deduce this Practice.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> did in like manner lay his Hands upon ſome baptiz'd Perſons at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Acts 19. 6. of which he minds them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 13. And when the Fundamentals of Religion are reckon'd up, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 1, 2. among them is plac'd the laying on of Hands, which in regard it follows Baptiſm, and is a Doctrine to be taught young Beginners, it is moſt likely to be meant of Confirmation, and is ſo interpreted by the Fathers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Was not this Apoſtolical uſage to ceaſe when Miraculous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations did not accompany it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Holy Spirit is to abide in the Church for ever, and Chriſtians have and need it now as really and effectually to the Purpoſes of Sanctification as any had it then; therefore there is no reaſon that the Rite of Communicating it ſhould ceaſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Church did in every Age continue this Cuſtom of Confirming after Baptiſm; which proves that they did not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it was a Temporary Inſtitution, to reject it therefore is to condemn the univerſal Practice of the Church, to which certainly a very great Deference is due.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Perſon to be confirm'd, interrogated, or ask'd the Queſtion, <hi>Do you here,</hi> &amp;c?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it gives the Party to be obliged opportunity to conſider what he is to bind himſelf unto, and ſo may give a deliberate Anſwer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:103580:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is one Godfather, or Godmother, peculiarly requir'd to be preſent?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For greater Security, as a Pledge of Sincerity, and to be a continual Monitor to keep the Vow, as well as a Witneſs of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe ſhort Verſes and Anſwers uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Upon the hearing of the Perſons good Confeſſion, the whole Church expreſs their Joy and their Deſires that it may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in ſome of the Words of <hi>David</hi>'s Pſalms, which are very properly inſerted here, that the whole Congregation may join in the Profeſſion of their Faith in God, In giving Glory to him, and in begging Acceptance from him, and the laſt Phraſe is doubled, to ſhew the vehement Deſire and fervent Affections of the Petitioners.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> If we have received the Holy Spirit in Baptiſm, why do we pray for it in this Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Baptiſm the Holy Spirit gives what is ſufficient to make us Innocent, but in Confirmation it gives increaſe and makes us gracious, according to which Ancient Doctrine, the Prayer is compos'd to Acknowledge the former Gift, and then to Petition for the Second.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Ceremony of laying on Hands uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is one of the moſt ancient Ceremonies in the World, obſerv'd by <hi>Jacob</hi> in giving his Bleſſing, and uſed by our Lord Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Rite perform'd by a Biſhop?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our Church is careful to keep to the Apoſtolical Pattern, in the Perſon as well as in the Ceremony; becauſe, tho' <hi>Philip</hi> had Liberty both to Preach and Baptize, yet the Apoſtles only could confirm, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 14, 15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This peculiar Privilege of Confirming, reſerv'd to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, is apt to beget a greater Veneration of it in the Minds of devout People, and to make them expect nobler Effects from that Office, which none but the Higheſt Miniſter of Religion can celebrate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What may be ſignified by this Rite?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That the Lord will ſtretch out his Hand to defend us againſt all our Spiritual Enemies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Communion Service.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is the <hi>Communion-Table</hi> ſo called by ſome, and by others the <hi>Altar?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is called an <hi>Altar,</hi> becauſe the Holy Euchariſt being conſidered as a Sacrifice, we offer up the Commemoration of that Sacrifice, which was offered upon the Croſs.</p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:103580:25"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. We offer with the Action Prayers to God for all good things, and we need not fear to call the whole Action by the Name of a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> ſeeing part of it is an Oblation to God of hearty Prayers, and it is not unuſual for that to be ſaid of the whole that is exactly true but of one part; and as the word <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> may be uſed without danger, ſo alſo the Ancient Church did underſtand it. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Patrick.</p>
                  <p>And it's called a <hi>Table,</hi> the Euchariſt being conſidered as a Sacrament; which is nothing elſe, but a Diſtribution and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Sacrifice to the Receivers, and the proper uſe of a Table is to ſet Food upon, and to entertain Gueſts, both which are applicable to this.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is part of the Communion-Service uſed when there is no Communion?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Church hereby doth mind us of what ſhe deſires and labours toward, <hi>viz.</hi> Our more frequent Acceſs or coming to that holy Table.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. Becauſe in the ancient Church the Altar was the place where they offered up their Prayers, to ſignifie that they offer'd them up only in the vertue of the Sacrifice of Chriſt, and that the very remembrance of this Sacrifice in the Lord's Supper, and by vertue of its Inſtitution, did render their Prayers prevalent and acceptable to God. <hi>Dr.</hi> Sherlock.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Did our Lord and Saviour inſtitute any one Method or Form of Adminiſtration?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: But left it to the Wiſdom and Piety of the Church, whoſe Edicts, or Injunctions, we are bound to obey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How many parts doth this Communion Office conſiſt of?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Four: Firſt, a more general Preparation to the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; and is either common to the whole Congregation in the Exerciſe of,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Repentance, by the Lord's Prayer, the Collect for Purity, and the Ten Commandments.</item>
                     <item>2. Holy Deſires, by the Collects for the King, and the Day.</item>
                     <item>3. Of Obedience, by the hearing of the Epiſtle and Goſpel.</item>
                     <item>4. Of Faith, by repeating the Creed.</item>
                     <item>5. Of Charity, by the Offertory and the Prayer for the Holy Catholick Church.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Or elſe, this general Preparation is proper to thoſe, who ought to communicate, <hi>viz.</hi> The Warning before the Communion, and the Exhortation to it.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Here is the more immediate Preparation contained. 1. In the proper Inſtructions, in the Exhortation at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and the immediate Invitation. 2. The Form of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging our Offences in the Confeſſion. And, 3. The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:103580:25"/> means of enſuring our Pardon, by the Abſolution and Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. And, 4. The exciting our Love and Gratitude, in the Preface and Hymn called the <hi>Triſagium,</hi> from repeating <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> three times one after another.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Here is the Celebration of the Myſtery, conſiſting of, 1. The Communicant's humble approach in the Addreſs. 2. The Miniſter's bleſſing the Elements in the Prayer of Conſecration, and his diſtributing them according to the Form of Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Laſtly, Here is the Poſt-Communion, containing Prayers and Vows, in the Lord's Prayer, and in the firſt and ſecond Prayers after the Communion; and containing Praiſes and Thankſgiving in the <hi>Glory be to God on high,</hi> &amp;c. And laſtly, the Diſmiſſion by the final Bleſſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Lord's Prayer begin this Service?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This holy Sacrament, and this Divine Prayer had one and the ſame Author, and therefore the Lord's Prayer is the moſt proper Preface to the Lord's Supper, and very ſuitable to that great Myſtery.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. Becauſe the Lord's Prayer uſed to be ſaid in every Office, and the Communion Service, the Litany, the Prayers, Leſſons and Collects are all ſeveral Offices, and uſed heretofore to be ſaid in our Churches at ſeveral times.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Collect for <hi>Purity</hi> premiſed before the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is both a very fit Introduction to the Communion-Service, and a proper Preface to the repeating of the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Commandments rehearſed in the Communion-Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In our Baptiſm we ſolemnly vowed to keep them, and at every Communion we renew that Vow, therefore it is very fit we ſhould have the Commandments repeated now, when we are going to make a freſh engagement to obſerve them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And ſince we are to confeſs all our Sins before we come to the bleſſed Sacrament of Pardon, the Church holds out this Glaſs unto us, by which we may diſcover our Offences.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Hath God given us no more than Ten <hi>Rules of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> There are no more requiſite than theſe, in reference to all Moral Actions, as being the Summary and general Heads under which are comprehended all the Duties we are to do in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and all the Sins we are to avoid; but there are other Poſitive Precepts to which our Obedience is required. God himſelf firſt divided this Law into Two Tables; The firſt Four
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:103580:26"/> contain our Duty to God, and the ſix Laſt our Duty to our Neighbour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are the Duties required, and the Sins forbidden in each Commandment?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In the Firſt Commandment, we are taught to have a right object of our Worſhip, to take the true God for our only God, and to Worſhip and Glorifie him accordingly. And we are forbidden Apoſtacy, Deifying the Creatures, and Diſtruſt of the true God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In the Second Commandment, we learn the right Means or Matter of our Worſhip; and it requires that we ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God with ſuch Worſhip as he has appointed in his Word ſuitable to his Nature.</p>
                  <p>And it forbids Idolatry, Superſtition, and all carnal and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Worſhip.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the Third Commandment, we learn the right Manner of our Worſhip, and it requires us devoutly to perform every part of Divine Worſhip, and reverently to uſe every thing which nearly relates to God.</p>
                  <p>It forbids Blaſphemy, Vain and falſe Oaths, Curſing, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faning holy Things, and Sacrilege.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. In the Fourth Commandment, we are taught the Solemn time of our Worſhip, and it enjoins us to <hi>keep holy the Seventh Day,</hi> (call'd by Chriſtians the <hi>Lord's-Day)</hi> and obſerved by us in memory of Chriſt's Reſurrection: for (as the learned Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Bramhal</hi> remarks) If the Memory of the old Creation, and God's reſting upon the Seventh Day, had ſuch an Influence upon the firſt Patriarchs, that it is piouſly believed by ſome, that they did freely without any Commandment obſerve that Day of Reſt according to the Example of God; Why ſhould not Chriſtians hallow the Day of Chriſt's Reſurrection, in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of Man's Redemption (or the New Creation compleated upon that Day by Chriſt) by ſpending it in worſhipping God both in Publick and in Private, or in Works of Neceſſity and Mercy.</p>
                  <p>And it forbids Neglect of the Publick Service on <hi>Sunday</hi> and other Holy Days, and ſpending thoſe times in Sin and Vanity, and gives us the Reaſons why we ſhould obey this Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> God's allowing Six Days for our own Employment, and his Challenging a Special Propriety in the Seventh, and his own Examples, and his Bleſſing and Sanctifying the Seventh Day.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. In the Fifth Commandment, we are taught our Duty to our Neighbour, with reſpect to their Perſons in all our Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: Natural, as Parents and Children; Civil, as Kings and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103580:26"/> Subjects; Religious, as Miniſters and People; Domeſtick, as Maſters and Servants; as likewiſe, of Inferiours to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours.</p>
                  <p>And it forbids Superiours Pride, Negligence, and Evil Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and Inferiours Diſobedience, Contempt and Reſiſting.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Sixth Commandment requires all lawful Endeavours to preſerve our own, and our Neighbours Life and Health,</p>
                  <p>And forbids Killing others, Challenging, Anger, Cruelty and Revenge.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Seventh Commandment, enjoins us Chaſtity in Heart, Speech and Behaviour,</p>
                  <p>And forbids actual Defiling of thoſe that are Married or Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and wanton Thoughts, Words, Geſtures, and the occaſion of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Gluttony and Drunkenneſs.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Eighth Commandment, requires the lawful furthering of our own and our Neighbours Wealth and outward Eſtate,</p>
                  <p>And forbids Thieving, Cheating, Unjuſt Detaining, Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the occaſions of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Idleneſs and Prodigality.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The Ninth Commandment, enjoins the Speaking of Truth, and the promoting our own and others good Name,</p>
                  <p>And forbids all falſe Evidence, Lying, Slandering, Tale-bearing and Flattery.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. The Tenth Commandment, requires our being content with our own Condition, and rejoicing at our Neighbours Welfare,</p>
                  <p>And it forbids an inordinate or unlawful Deſire of any thing that is our Neighbours, Envy, or grieving at others Good, and diſcontent with our own Condition.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe I underſtand it will be more acceptable to ſome (whoſe Judgment I highly value and eſteem) to give an Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation according to that made in our Church Catechiſm, by applying ſeverally to each Commandment what is there ſet down altogether. I have therefore likewiſe here inſerted it as well as I could in the Churches Words.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the firſt Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To have the One only true God for our God, and <hi>to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in him and to fear him, and to love him with all my Heart, and all my Mind, and all my Strength.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the ſecond Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not to make any bodily Image, or likeneſs of God, or to worſhip any Image for God, but to worſhip him only, by <hi>calling upon his Holy Name</hi> in my Prayers and Praiſes, and <hi>put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my whole truſt in him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the third Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. To honour God's Holy Name and his Word,</hi> and not to abuſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:103580:27"/> it by Swearing falſely, or cauſeleſly, or ſpeaking irreverently of either.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the fourth Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſet apart the Firſt Day of the Week to God's Worſhip and Service in memory of Chriſt's riſing from the Dead, to ceaſe and reſt from Sin, and to <hi>ſerve God truly</hi> and faithfully <hi>all the days of my Life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the fifth Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>A. To love, honour and ſuccour my Father and my Mother, to honour and obey the King, and all that are put in Authority under him, to ſubmit my ſelf to all my Governours, Teachers, Spiritual Paſtors and Maſters, and to order my ſelf lowly and reverently to all my Betters?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the ſixth Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not by Violence to take away my own or another's Life, <hi>to bear no Malice or Hatred in my heart, and to hurt nobody by ill Words or Deeds.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the ſeventh Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Not to lie Carnally with any Woman without lawful Marriage, but to <hi>keep my body in Soberneſs, Temperance and Chaſtity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the eighth Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>A. To be true and juſt in all my dealings, and to keep my hands from picking and ſtealing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the ninth Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To keep my Tongue from evil ſpeaking, <hi>lying and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering,</hi> and to ſpeak the truth from my Heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What doth the tenth Commandment require?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A. Not to Covet nor deſire other Mens Goods, but to learn and labour truly to get my own Living,</hi> and to do my Duty in <hi>that ſtate of Life into</hi> which it ſhall pleaſe <hi>God to call me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The General Rule for theſe Commandments is, that where a Duty is commanded, there the contrary Sin is forbidden; and ſo on the other ſide, where a Sin is forbidden, there the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Duty is commanded.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Miniſter rehearſe the Commandments Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew his Authority; here is God ſpeaking by the Prieſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do the People kncel all the time, and beg mercy?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they have offended againſt all the Commandments, therefore they kneel down as Criminals ought to do, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beſeech Pardon; and that we may never commit the like again, we pray, that the Lord would incline our hearts to keep theſe Laws; and ſo the Law may be a means of our Repentance and Reformation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:103580:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we pray for the King immediately after the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque Tabulae,</hi> the Defender of both Tables.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Prayer for the King juſt before the daily Collect?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe that when we have prayed for outward Proſperity to the Church, the conſequent of the King's Welfare, we may in the Collect pray for inward Grace, to make it compleatly happy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How long have the Collects been fixed to thoſe very <hi>Sundays,</hi> on which we now uſe them?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Above Twelve Hundred Years.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Epiſtle read firſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As being the Word of the Servant appointed to perſonate the Law, preceding the Goſpel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Goſpel follow?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> As being the Word of our great Maſter, therefore when the Miniſter is about to read, all the People ſtand up, to expreſs a more than ordinary reverence to it; and to give Glory to God before it's read, and Thanks to God after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is that Creed which is rehearſed after the Goſpel called the <hi>Nicene Creed?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it was for the moſt part framed at the great <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> of <hi>Nice;</hi> the ſame in ſubſtance with the Apoſtles Creed, but doth more largely condemn all Hereſies; therefore is fitly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>join'd to be recited before the Sacrament.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Sentences uſed at the beginning of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſtir us up more effectually to give bountifully.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How is our Charity to be expreſs'd?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Three Ways, <hi>viz.</hi> by Giving, Praying, and Forgiving.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Where have we Directions for each of theſe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For <hi>Giving,</hi> in the Sentences.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Prayer,</hi> in the Prayer for the Church Militant.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Forgiving,</hi> in the general Warning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How often ought we to receive?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It ſeems very probable from the Inſtitution of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that our Saviour deſign'd it ſhould be part of God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in all the ſolemn Aſſemblies of Chriſtians: And we ſhew our Love by coming freely and frequently, as often as we have an Opportunity; for Publick Worſhip is very lame and imperfect without it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Deſign of the Exhortations, and of the Invitation before the Sacrament?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The former is to increaſe the Number, and the latter to rectifie the Diſpoſitions of the Communicants.</p>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:103580:28"/>
                  <p>In the Invitation (the Gueſts being prepared) the Prieſt invites them to come near with Fear and Faith; and that God may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept them, he repeats thoſe Graces with which they muſt be ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>viz.</hi> Repentance, Charity, and Holy Purpoſes, ſhewing them what is the firſt Duty to be done, <hi>viz.</hi> making an humble Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion upon their Knees.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Confeſſion here uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Since Chriſt's Sufferings are here remembred, we muſt own our Sins, which were the Cauſe of them. And ſince we hope for Pardon, we ought with Shame and Sorrow firſt to own our Tranſgreſſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Form of Abſolution here uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Leſt our Guilt ſhould terrifie us from coming to this Holy Table, the Prieſt pronounceth Abſolution in Chriſt's Name, in the Form of a Prayer or Benediction, which ought to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with Faith and Gratitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Sentences of Scripture uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Church hath choſen theſe Sentences to confirm the Faith, and revive the Hope of poor Penitents, and they are thoſe very Promiſes on which the foregoing Abſolution is grounded; ſo that unleſs they doubt the Truth of God's Word, they muſt believe theſe Promiſes of Mercy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Reſponſes, Prefaces, and Triſagium here appointed to be uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This Sacrament is a Feaſt of Joy and Thankſgiving, and the Nature of the Euchariſt requires ſome Acts of Praiſe and Gratitude.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Here the Prieſt admoniſheth us to Praiſe God, in the Reſponſes.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And gives the Reaſon of it in the Prefaces.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And joins with us in doing of it in the Triſagium, which becauſe the Word <hi>Holy</hi> is Thrice repeated, was by the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſo called?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are the Angels mentioned in this Hymn?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the Chriſtian Church believed the Angels were preſent in Chriſtian Aſſemblies, therefore thought it ſit, that Men ſhould join with them in this Heavenly Song, over the Memorial of our Redemption.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Prieſt on great Feſtivals add other Prefaces?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> They contain proper Reaſons for our Thankſgiving on thoſe ſpecial Occaſions; and the Decay of Devotion, letting fall the Primitive and Apoſtolical Life of Weekly Communions, and the People receiving but at the great Feſtivals, the Church there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore added to the General Prefaces ſome ſpecial ones, relating to the peculiar Mercy of that Feaſt on which they did commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:103580:28"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> What Reaſon for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Addreſs, or the Collect which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ns thus, <hi>We do not preſume to come to this thy Table,</hi> &amp;c?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The nearer we come to God the more Holy we ought to be, and when we are juſt going to make ſo immediate Approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, our very Joy muſt be tempered with Humility, and we muſt excuſe our own Unworthineſs?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Prayer of Conſecration uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Imitation of our Lord and Saviour and his Apoſtles, all the Churches in the World have uſed ſuch a Form: We do not eat our common Food, without firſt praying for a Bleſſing on it, which Pious Cuſtom is ſo univerſal, that it is certainly a piece of natural Religion; much more then are we obliged before we eat and drink, this Bread and Wine which <hi>Chriſt</hi> deſigned to ſet forth the Myſtery of his Death to conſecrate and ſet it apart by a ſolemn Prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Words are they which properly make the Conſecration?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Words of our Saviour's Inſtitution pronounced by a lawful Prieſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do the People join with the Prieſt in ſaying, <hi>Amen?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Teſtimony of their Faith, that the Elements are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come what Chriſt made and intended them to be; that they have the Merits of his Sacrifice annexed to them by his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do the Communicants receive the Holy Symbols kneeling?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To expreſs their Humility, and the Senſe, they have of their own Unworthineſs, and that they may be in a poſture of Prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Of how many Particulars do the Words conſiſt, which the Prieſt uſeth when he delivereth the Bread and Wine?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Three: 1. Inſtruction declaring what it is, <hi>viz.</hi> The Body of our Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Blood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Prayer; deſiring this Communication of them to us may preſerve our Bodies and Souls unto everlaſting Life.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Direction, what we are to do, <hi>viz.</hi> Take, Eat, Drink, this in remembrance that Chriſt died, and his Blood was ſhed for us, and to feed on him in our Hearts by Faith with Thankſgiving, and to be Thankful; The whole Form together comes as nigh our Lord's own Words in his Adminiſtring this his laſt Supper, as can well be.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is this Feaſt call'd the <hi>Lord's Supper?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it was inſtituted by our Lord Jeſus at that time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Does it not ſeem to be improper to call it the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> when it is in moſt Churches celebrated in the Morning?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: The Celebration of this Feaſt at Supper, was but a Circumſtantial thing, and therefore the Church is not oblig'd
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103580:29"/> to keep it; yet becauſe it is ſtill in imitation of Chriſt's Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> and that Supper is religiouſly remembred in it, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Eſſential things, together with the ſcope, drift and deſign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> are ſtill preſerved, it is not unfitly called the <hi>Lord's Supper</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>; yet it is, and may be lawfully call'd and expreſs'd by other Names, and this the Chriſtian Churches have done; Some call it a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> taking the Name from the Oaths that the <hi>Roman</hi> Soldiers took, of Truth and Fidelity, and here we Vow Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance and Fidelity to our Lord Jeſus. Others call it a <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> becauſe we are hereby ty'd in a Bond of Mutual Love, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of the ſame Bread, are fellow Members of the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, and have Communion with Chriſt their Head, and enjoy all the ſame Benefits of his Death and Sufferings. Many other Names are appropriated to this Myſtery.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why did our Lord Jeſus make uſe of the Night in inſtituting of it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it was to ſucceed in the Place of the Paſſover, which according to Cuſtom, was Eaten at Night; but the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ceaſing with the Typical Paſſover, the Chriſtian Church celebrates it at all Seaſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> uſe Bread with Leaven in the Holy Sacrament, whereas our Saviour at the firſt Inſtitution made uſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleaven'd Bread?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Our Lord made uſe of Unleaven'd Bread, becauſe there was no other to be had at that time; but it being a thing indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and the Subſtance or Eſſence of the Sacrament not at all prejudic'd by it, the Church makes uſe of Leavened Bread.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Communicant ſay <hi>Amen</hi> after the Prayer at the Delivery of the Bread and Wine?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> By it he profeſſeth his Faith of the preſence of Chriſt's Body and Blood in the Sacrament really, that is truly exhibited and preſent to the Faith of the Receiver.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Poſt <hi>Communion, or the Service after the Communion.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is the Feaſt concluded with Prayers and Hymns?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it was our Saviour's Practice, at its firſt Inſtitution.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Lord's Prayer the firſt part of this Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It's very fit that after we have received our Saviour into our Hearts, the firſt Words we ſpeak ſhould be <hi>His.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the Deſign of the other two Prayers?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> For the farther Exerciſe and Improvement of our Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the former conſiſts chiefly of Vows, and the latter of Praiſes
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:103580:29"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> and Thankſgiving with an humble Petition for the Grace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſeverance.</p>
                  <p>Q. <hi>What Reaſon for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the concluding Hymn?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> After ſuch high Favours and ſuch great Bleſſings recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it is fit and neceſſary we ſhould expreſs our Joy, and how can we welcome our Saviour more properly, than by the Hymn with which the Angels welcomed him into the World.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Bleſſing pronounced by the Prieſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Imitation of our Bleſſed Saviour, who took his Leave of his Diſciples with a Bleſſing, and this Form the Church took from St. <hi>Paul, Philip.</hi> 4. 7.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Matrimony.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is this Office performed by a Miniſter?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Marriage is the Bond as well as the Foundation of all Societies, which ought to be made ſacred and adopted into Religion, becauſe it's the Intereſt of Mankind it ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable, wherefore our Church appoints, That none but a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miniſter ſhall tie theſe Bonds, for the Covenant is made to God, and the Miniſter is God's Repreſentative to take the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and bleſs the Parties in God's Name.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What's meant by Bans, or Banes of Matrimony?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Matrimonial Contracts, or Decrees. <hi>Ban</hi> comes from a <hi>Saxon</hi> word, which ſignifies a Proclamation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it ordered to be celebrated in the Morning?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe Men are moſt ſerious at that Time, and the better to prevent Clandeſtine Marriages, the Church orders it to be made in the Day-time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is it required that Marriages be celebrated in the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That this Rite may be more ſolemn, the Church being the Place of God's ſpecial Preſence before whom this Covenant is made, and the ſacredneſs of the Place ſhould make them more reverent in entring into it, and more careful in keeping it?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the State of Matrimony called Holy?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe it is a holy and important Work, an Ordinance of God the Father, an Eſtate much reſpected by God the Son, and highly commended by God the Holy Ghoſt, in the Mouths of the Apoſtles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are the Ends of Matrimony?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Procreation, a Remedy againſt Sin, and a mutual Help to each other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is that Charge given, That if the Perſons to be joined, <hi>Know any Impediment,</hi> &amp;c?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe if there be any Impediment which they conceal
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:103580:30"/> from the Prieſt, they muſt either live in perpetual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeparated by an endleſs Divorce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are the Impediments to a Marriage?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> A preceding Marriage, or ſolemn Precontract.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If the Parties be of near Kindred.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Want of the Conſent of Parents, or Guardians in Caſe of Minority.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why muſt Women be given?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 1. After the Example of God in Paradiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. 22. <hi>(Dr.</hi> Hammond.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. In Ancient Times (ſaith the Learned and Judicious Mr. <hi>Hooker) All Women which had not Husbands, or Fathers to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them, had their Tutors,</hi> without whoſe Authority there was no Act which they did warrantable, and for this cauſe they were in Marriage delivered unto their Husbands by others, which Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom retained hath ſtill this Uſe, that it puts Women in Mind of a Duty, whereto the imbecillity or weakneſs of their Sex doth bind them, namely, to be always directed and guided by others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 3. However, it's a Decent Cuſtom whether this was the Firſt Cauſe or no: For a Woman cannot in Modeſty offer her ſelf, but ſhould rather be led by the Hand of another, and given by him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Prieſt join the Right Hand?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe they are generally uſed in <hi>plighting our Troth,</hi> by which Phraſe is meant, laying our Truth to pledge, or engaging our Faith.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is a Ring given?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To be a viſible and laſting Token, and Remembrance of this Covenant. The Matter is Gold, to ſignifie how noble and durable our Affection is. The Form is round, being the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereſt Figure to unite things ſeparated, and to imply our Reſpect ſhall never have an end; and the Place is on the Fourth Finger of the Left Hand, where is a Vein that comes directly from the Heart, and where it may be always in View, and being a Finger leaſt uſed, it may be leſs ſubject to be worn out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What's the meaning of thoſe Words, <hi>With this Ring I thee wed.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This is a Pledge of that Covenant of Matrimony which I juſt now make with thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What are the Rights accruing to the Wife by this Covenant of Matrimony?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhare in all the Honours belonging to the Man's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which is the meaning of thoſe Words, <hi>With my Body I thee worſhip.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. To have an Intereſt in his Eſtate, ſignified by that Phraſe,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103580:30"/> 
                     <hi>With all my worldly Goods I thee endow,</hi> and it was an ancient Uſage to lay down a Summ of Money on the Book, which the Prieſt delivers the Wife, to give her Livery and Seiſing of her Husband's Eſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>Q. <hi>What do thoſe Words ſignifie,</hi> In the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Man makes this Covenant by his Chriſtianity, and before the Trinity, as Witneſſes thereto, who, if he break, will be the Avenger of this Perjury; for theſe Words calling God to Witneſs, turn this Promiſe into a ſolemn and ſacred Oath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebecca</hi> propoſed as Examples?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe <hi>Iſaac</hi> kept him only to this One Wife, when he might have had more.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How is this Matrimonial Covenant ratified?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Prieſt pronouncing them to be Man and Wife toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>In the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Amen, doth ſet God's Seal to this Holy and Religious compact to make it perfect and compleat, ſo that the Union is ſacred, invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, and never to be diſſolved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> When God made the Society of Marriage, why was Man made Superiour?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe he knew Equality would breed Confuſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is Man commanded to Honour his Wife?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Meaning is, That he muſt give Reſpect and Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſuitable to her Degree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Rubrick after this Office, adviſe the Perſons who are married to receive the Holy Communion, either that Day, or as ſoon after as is poſſible?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To confirm their Vows to each other by the Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, and to bind themſelves more ſtrictly to their ſeveral Duties.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Viſitation of the Sick.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> TO whom doth this Duty eſpecially belong?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To the Clergy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Have we any Command in Holy Scripture for it?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Yes: In St. <hi>James</hi> 5. 14, 15. <hi>Is any ſick among you? Let him call for the Elders of the Church, and let them pray over him, anointing him with Oil,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are not the ſick now anointed with Oil?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In St. <hi>James</hi>'s Time, as long as the miraculous Gift of Healing continued, it was uſed; not to convey Grace to the Soul, but to work a miraculous Cure, which was the uſual Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: But the Power and Gift being ceaſed, the Church hath left off the Oil, which was the Sign, but we retain all the Subſtantial Parts of this Office.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:103580:31"/>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Prieſt when he enters the ſick Man's Houſe, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute all that are in it with thoſe Words, <hi>Peace be to this Houſe?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe our Lord and Saviour ordered his Diſciples to uſe it, when they went to cure both Souls and Bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What's the Meaning of that Phraſe?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is a Pious Wiſh for the Health and Proſperity of all that dwell in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhy is the Exhortation uſed?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we are commanded by God, not only to pray for, but to ſupport the Weak, by Comfort, Counſel, and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat are the Duties we are exhorted to?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Repentance, Charity, and Confeſſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> VVhat doth the Exhortation conſiſt of?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Of Inſtruction concerning the Author of Afflictions; the End why they are ſent, the Manner how we muſt bear them, the Benefit of ſo doing, with Exhortations to ſeveral Graces and Duties.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Prieſt repeat the Creed, and the Sick Man ſay it after him?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe we vowed in Baptiſm, we would <hi>believe all the Articles of our Chriſtian Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Sick Man declares his ſtedfaſt Faith to every Article, to ſhew he dies a true Chriſtian, and a ſound Member of the Holy Catholick Church: And to arm himſelf with this Shield againſt the Fear of Death, and the Arguments Satan may uſe to bring him to Deſpair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Abſolution uſed in this Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe St. <hi>James</hi> expreſly requires it to be given to a Sick Penitent, after the Prieſt hath prayed over him; and ſince <hi>Chriſt</hi> left ſuch a Power with his Church, there is never more need to uſe it than now: This is the Higheſt Form of Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion uſed by this Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How doth the Prieſt cloſe this Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> He doth it with giving the Sick a Bleſſing at the parting by 3. Solemn Forms, the firſt directed to God the Son, the ſecond is a Formal Bleſſing in the Name of God the Father, and the laſt is an Addreſs to the whole Trinity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Church think it neceſſary that the ſick Man ſhould receive the Communion?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It's the higheſt Myſtery of Religion and fitteſt for thoſe who are by Sickneſs put into a Heavenly Frame, and are neareſt to Perfection.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It's God's Seal of Remiſſion to all that receive it with Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitence and Faith.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:103580:31"/>
                  <p n="3"> 3. It arms them againſt the Fear of Death, by ſetting <hi>Jeſus</hi> before them, who died for them, and hath pulled out the Sting of Death.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It aſſures them of their Reſurrection by making them Members of Chriſt's Body.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. It declares they die in the Peace and the Communion of the true Church.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Burial of the Dead.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> HATH the Burial of the Dead been the Practice of all Nations?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Care of the Bodies deceaſed hath been accounted a Pious thing among all Nations, tho' the Manner hath been diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſome Burning, others Burying, and other Embalming their Dead.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Regard had the Jews and Primitive Chriſtians for Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Jews counted it an eminent kind of Mercy, and the Primitive Chriſtians were famous for their Charity, in burying the Bodies not of their Friends only, but of their very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Did any believe that the Dead were the better for what was done to their Bodies?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> No: Divers of the Philoſophers cared not whether they were buried or no; and ſome of the Martyrs deſpiſed their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors threatning them with want of a Grave?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What then are the true Reaſons for Burials?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> That our Friends Bodies may not be a Prey to Birds and Beaſts.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Shame of nature may not be expos'd.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That all may return to their proper Place, and be covered with the Skirt of their Mother, the Earth. To which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians add three more Reaſons;</p>
                  <p>Becauſe Men are made after God's Image.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And as they were Chriſtians their Bodies were the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And ſhall be raiſed again, and made glorious.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do we Bury in the Church, or Church-Yard?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To put thoſe in mind of their Mortality, who come to the Houſe of Prayer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Time generally in the Night?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The firſt Chriſtians were forced ſo to Bury, and later Ages imitated them, only adding divers Lights, to ſhew their Hope of the Party's being gone to Light everlaſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:103580:32"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why do Friends follow the Corps to the Grave?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To mind them that they muſt ſhortly follow the deceaſed in the ſame Path of Death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why doth the Prieſt meet at the Church gate in his Surplice?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To allay the Sorrow which naturally ſeizeth on us, when we follow a dear Friend to the Grave the Prieſt meets us in white, the Colour of Joy, in imitation of the Angels, who go out in white Garments to receive the Soul, ſo doth he to receive the body of the faithful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> 2. This is the Attire which is appointed for the Miniſter in the Performance of all his Publick offices.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Sentences ſaid in the Way?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To excite the Company to Faith, Patience and Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Body brought into the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſhew the Party died in the Communion thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What is the meaning of thoſe words, in ſure and certain hope of the Reſurrection to Eternal Life.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> This is not ſpoken of the Party deceaſed, but of the belief of the Standers by of this Article themſelves, and therefore we ſay afterward, who ſhall change <hi>our vile</hi> body, and not of the Party deceaſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are Prayers ſaid at the Grave?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> Since the ſight of that Place and of the Corps now ready to be put into it, is wont to make great Impreſſions on us; the Church takes this occaſion to fit us with Devotions at the Grave.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To ſhew the peculiar hope of the Church, of the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Dead.</p>
                  <p>In the manner of dumb Funerals, what one thing is there, whereby the World may perceive we are Chriſtians; there being in thoſe dumb Shows nothing but what Heathens and Pagans do.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Churching of Women.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHY is the Woman ordered to come to Church, and offer up her publick Praiſes?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Birth of Man is little leſs than a Miracle, and leſt the Frequency ſhould diminiſh our Senſe of it, the Woman who hath received this wonderful Mercy is ordered to come to Church, and offer up her publick Praiſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Reaſon for this Command of the Church?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> The Original is from the Law of <hi>Moſes, Levit.</hi> 12. which commands all Women after they had born a Child, to come to the Houſe of God within a certain number of days, and with a Sacrifice to praiſe God for this great Mercy, and although the Ceremonial Reaſon be ceaſed, yet the Obligation to make a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:103580:32"/> publick Acknowledgment of ſo eminent a Favour remains ſtill and in all Ages Chriſtian Mothers have obſerved this holy Rite.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why is the Church the Place appointed to do this in?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It muſt be done thus publickly.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For God's Honour.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To ſatisfy the Womans Duty, who is bound to let God's Goodneſs be ſhewed forth, that others may learn to truſt in him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By this means many are brought to join in God's Praiſes for ſo publick a Mercy; and therefore to do this in a private Houſe is abſurd, and contrary to the main end of the Office.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Commination.</head>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> WHAT was the Reaſon and Occaſion of compoſing this Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> To ſupply the want of Primitive Diſcipline, that every Man may judge himſelf, ſince the Church now judgeth ſo few Offenders.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Why are thoſe Sentences of God's Curſing againſt impenitent Sinners read?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> In Imitation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who were appointed by God yearly to obſerve this Office.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> Doth not he that ſays <hi>Amen</hi> wiſh a Curſe to himſelf?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It is no Adverb of Wiſhing, it ſignifies no more than an Aſſent to the truth of that to which it is added.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe may we make of this Office?</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.</hi> It may be uſeful to make us flee ſuch Vices, and repent of them, which here are mentioned; ſince we acknowledge the Curſe and Vengeance of God doth deſervedly follow ſuch Sins and Sinners.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> What Days in the Week are ſet apart for Publick Worſhip throughout the World?</head>
                  <p>A.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>Sunday, <hi>or the</hi> Lord's Day, <hi>is obſerv'd by</hi> Chriſtians.</item>
                     <item>Monday <hi>by the</hi> Grecians.</item>
                     <item>Tueſday <hi>by the</hi> Perſians.</item>
                     <item>Wedneſday <hi>by the</hi> Aſſyrians.</item>
                     <item>Thurſday <hi>by the</hi> Egyptians.</item>
                     <item>Friday <hi>by the</hi> Turks.</item>
                     <item>Saturday <hi>by the</hi> Jews.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction_to_the_Bible">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:103580:33"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Account of the Titles of all the Books of the</hi> Old <hi>and</hi> New Teſtament, <hi>and why they are ſtil'd</hi> Canonical, <hi>and the meaning of the Word</hi> Apocryphal, <hi>which Title is given to thoſe Books which are not Received into the Canon.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="Old" type="Testament">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Old Teſtament <hi>or</hi> Covenant.</head>
               <p>THE Books in Holy Scripture are call'd <hi>Canonical,</hi> becauſe according to Rule and Order they have been received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Canon; that is, into the Number of thoſe Writings which are unqueſtionably acknowledged to be the Writings of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and <hi>Holy Men</hi> inſpired in the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> or <hi>Covenant;</hi> And of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and Diſciples of Chriſt in the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> or <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Word in <hi>Greek</hi> which is tranſlated <hi>Teſtament,</hi> ſignifies both a <hi>Covenant,</hi> and a <hi>Teſtament;</hi> Both the Words in the Title of the <hi>Holy Bible</hi> may be uſed,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of <hi>Covenant,</hi> as being moſt agreeable to the uſe of the Word in the <hi>Sacred Dialect,</hi> and moſt agreeable to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which is the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That Word of a <hi>Teſtament</hi> alſo, wherein the Chriſtian's Inheritance is ſealed to him as to a <hi>Son</hi> and <hi>Heir</hi> of <hi>God</hi>'s, and wherein the Death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as of a <hi>Teſtator,</hi> is ſet down at large by way of Story, and as it is applicable to our Benefit.</p>
               <div n="Pentateuch" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of the</hi> Pentateuch.</head>
                  <p>THE Five firſt Books in the beginning of the Holy Bible, <hi>viz. Geneſis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, Deuteronomy,</hi> were Penned by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and called the <hi>Pentateuch;</hi> which word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Volume of Five Books.</p>
                  <div n="Genesis" type="book">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Geneſis.</head>
                     <p>This Firſt Book of <hi>Moſes</hi> contains the Hiſtory of the Creation of the World, particularly of the Making of Man, with which it begins; and the Genealogy of the Patriarchs, down to the Death of <hi>Joſeph</hi> where it ends, with relation whereunto it is very fitly called <hi>Geneſis,</hi> that Greek word very properly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Original or firſt Formation of theſe things: It com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends an Hiſtory of 2369 Years, or thereabout in the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many Learned Writers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Exodus" type="book">
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:103580:33"/>
                     <head>Exodus.</head>
                     <p>This Book hath its Name from the Principal Subject of it, <hi>viz.</hi> The Departure of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> For ſo the <hi>Greek</hi> word ſignifies, Going out, or Departing from one place to another. It contains an Hiſtory of about 145 Years from the Death of <hi>Joſeph</hi> to the Building of the Tabernacle, for it treats of ſeveral things which went before their departure, and which followed after it; but they all Relate to that and depend upon it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Leviticus" type="book">
                     <head>Leviticus.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Levi</hi> was the Third Son of <hi>Jacob,</hi> from him his Poſterity had the Name of <hi>Levites; Aaron,</hi> who with his Sons was called to the Prieſthood, was from him called a <hi>Levite,</hi> and the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood that was ſetled in that Family, is call'd <hi>Levitical;</hi> The Law relating to the diſcharge of the Prieſts Office, is called the <hi>Levitical Law,</hi> and upon that account, That Book of <hi>Moſes</hi> which more eſpecially treats of the Holy Rites and Services in which theſe Prieſts were by their Office imployed, is very fitly from the Subject Matter of it call'd <hi>Leviticus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Numbers" type="book">
                     <head>Numbers.</head>
                     <p>This Book is call'd <hi>Numbers</hi> from the Subject Matter which it begins withal, <hi>viz.</hi> An Account of the Number of the People of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Deuteronomy" type="book">
                     <head>Deuteronomy.</head>
                     <p>This Book is very fitly called <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> which in the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue imports a Repetition of the Law; There being in this Divine Book a Repetition not only of many Facts which had paſſed before; but of many Laws alſo which were mentioned before.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <div n="Joshua" type="book">
                     <head>Joſhua.</head>
                     <p>This Book is ſo called, becauſe it containeth the Hiſtory of His Acts, in his Government, Conqueſts, dividing the Land, and ſetling of the State and Commonwealth of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as it is moſt probable) it was Penned by <hi>Joſhua,</hi> following here in the Example of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Predeceſſor: Howſoever ſome Paſſages could not be Penned by himſelf, as containing ſome thinks which were done after his Death; but were afterward inſerted by ſome Holy Men of God inſpired by the Spirit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Judges" type="book">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:103580:34"/>
                     <head>Judges.</head>
                     <p>This Book which ſeemeth to have been gathered by ſome Prophet out of the Publick Records, containeth the Hiſtory of the chief things which happened to the People of God after the Death of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> until the days of <hi>Eli</hi> the High Prieſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Ruth" type="book">
                     <head>Ruth.</head>
                     <p>This Book is an Addition to the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> and is call'd <hi>the Book of</hi> Ruth, becauſe ſhe is the chief Subject of this Story; the main Scope is to continue and declare the Genealogy of our Saviour Chriſt, deſcended of <hi>Boaz</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> and of <hi>Ruth</hi> a <hi>Moabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Gentile,</hi> to ſhew that He ſhould bring Salvation to all of every Nation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1 Samuel (1 Kings)" type="book">
                     <head>I. Samuel.</head>
                     <p>This Book was entituled with the Name of <hi>Samuel,</hi> not that he was the Author of it, but becauſe the firſt Eight Chapters chiefly reſpect him and the things done under his Government, and was written by one of his Diſciples, a Son of the Prophets, who in honour of his Maſter, call'd it by his Name.</p>
                     <p>And it is called <hi>The Firſt Book of the Kings,</hi> becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth a Relation of ſuch things as happened under the firſt King's Government.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2 Samuel (2 Kings)" type="book">
                     <head>II. Samuel.</head>
                     <p>This Book is a Continuation of the Hiſtory of God's People from <hi>Saul</hi>'s Death to the End of <hi>David</hi>'s Reign, and is the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of 40 Years.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1 Kings (3 Kings)" type="book">
                     <head>I. Kings.</head>
                     <p>This Book was made by one or more Prophets, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth the Sacred Hiſtory of <hi>Kings</hi> from the End of <hi>David</hi>'s Reign to the End of <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi>'s Reign; The Diviſion of the Twelve Tribes into Two Kingdoms; The Reign of the firſt Four Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> and Eight of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the Diviſion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2 Kings (4 Kings)" type="book">
                     <head>II. Kings.</head>
                     <p>This Book continueth the Hiſtory of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> to the Captivity of them both. Theſe Two Books of the <hi>Kings</hi> are diſtinguiſhed, not as if they contained Hiſtories of different Matters; but becauſe if all the Hiſtory of both Books had been Compiled in one Book, it would have ſeemed too great a Volume.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1-2 Chronicles" type="book">
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:103580:34"/>
                     <head>I. Chronicles.</head>
                     <p>This word <hi>Chronicle</hi> is a Regiſter of Acts done time after time; Theſe Two Books were of old Compiled in One, and contain an Hiſtory of 3457 Years at leaſt, from <hi>Adam</hi> to the Return of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity, 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 36. 22. And the Genealogy of <hi>David</hi>'s Poſterity, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 2. 19.</p>
                     <p>The Penman of theſe Two Books the ſame with that of <hi>Ezra,</hi> by which it appears they were Penned after the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Greek</hi> Title is <hi>Remainders</hi> which has relation to the Book of <hi>Kings,</hi> as if Theſe had gathered up what They had left out. In the Book of <hi>Kings</hi> there are References to the Book of <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles;</hi> But Theſe Sacred Books of <hi>Chronicles</hi> cannot be there meant, becauſe They were not then Penned, and many things referred to the Books of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> are not found in theſe Books.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Ezra" type="book">
                     <head>Ezra.</head>
                     <p>This Book is called <hi>Ezra,</hi> either becauſe a great part of it contains Memorable Acts of His; or (as is ſuppoſed) <hi>Ezra</hi> the Prieſt was the Penman after the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Nehemiah" type="book">
                     <head>Nehemiah.</head>
                     <p>This Book is called <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> becauſe He and his Acts are the chief Subject of the Book, and (as is ſuppoſed) Penned by <hi>Ezra.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Esther" type="book">
                     <head>Eſther.</head>
                     <p>This Title of <hi>Eſther</hi> is given to this Book in Memory of that Prudent and Pious Queen, who was an Inſtrument of great good to the Church of God; yet throughout the whole Book, not one Tittle of God is once ſet down.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Job" type="book">
                     <head>Job.</head>
                     <p>In the time of the Ancient Patriarchs before the giving of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> there lived in <hi>Arabia</hi> a Perſon of great Eminence, whoſe Name was <hi>Job;</hi> The Scope of the Book is to eſtabliſh the great Article of Providence, and thereby to preſerve us from Errour in thinking that God's Knowledge or his Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Providence and Government is like ours; which Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation being laid, nothing will ſeem hard to a Man, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever happens.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Psalms" type="book">
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:103580:35"/>
                     <head>Pſalms.</head>
                     <p>The Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> or <hi>Praiſes</hi> ſo call'd from the Major part, and they are called <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Pſalms,</hi> becauſe he made moſt of them, for there were ſeveral other Authors by whom ſome of them were compoſed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Proverbs" type="book">
                     <head>Proverbs.</head>
                     <p>King <hi>Solomon</hi> was the Author of this Book. The word <hi>Proverbs</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> denotes only any acute and excellent Saying, which is as worthy to be known by all, and to be in every ones Mouth as common Proverbs are: And in Holy Scripture the word is uſed for an eloquent Speech, or a pithy Sentence in a few words expreſſing much Senſe, A Profitable Inſtruction.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Ecclesiastes" type="book">
                     <head>Eccleſiaſtes.</head>
                     <p>The word <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> ſignifies the <hi>Preacher,</hi> and this Book which bears this Name was written by King <hi>Solomon</hi> in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining Age to ſignifie his Repentance.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Song of Solomon" type="book">
                     <head>The Song of Songs.</head>
                     <p>This Book is called the <hi>Canticles,</hi> which ſignifies a Song; and was compoſed by King <hi>Solomon</hi> in the beginning of his Reign.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="prophetic books" type="part">
                  <head>Of the Prophets.</head>
                  <p>Theſe Holy Men inſpired by God are ſo termed, becauſe they did foretel future Events by Divine Revelation; and Theſe whoſe Monuments we have ſeverally booked in Holy Scripture are Sixteen, whereof the Four former are called the <hi>Greater,</hi> in regard of the largeneſs of their Prophecies; The latter Twelve are called the <hi>Leſſer,</hi> in regard of the ſhortneſs of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies.</p>
                  <div n="Isaiah" type="book">
                     <head>Iſaiah.</head>
                     <p>This name <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is taken from the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> but our Ancient Verſions ſpeaking in Engliſh forms to Engliſh ears, following the <hi>Greek,</hi> do not amiſs render it <hi>Eſay,</hi> the word ſignifies <hi>God's Salvation;</hi> no unfit Title for him who ſo clearly and largely propheſied of Chriſt. This Prophet as in Place and Rank, ſo in order of time is, without queſtion, the Firſt of the four Larger or great Prophets. He is by the Ancients not undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly term'd, An Evangelical Prophet.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Jeremiah" type="book">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:103580:35"/>
                     <head>Jeremiah.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jeremiah</hi> was a Prieſt (which ſome of the other Prophets were not) before his entrance upon this extraordinary Employment of Prophecy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Lamentations" type="book">
                     <head>Lamentations.</head>
                     <p>This Book was compoſed by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in the time of the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonian</hi> Captivity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Ezekiel" type="book">
                     <head>Ezekiel.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ezekiel</hi> of the Prieſtly Race, compoſed this Prophecy in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> to which he was carried Captive.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Daniel" type="book">
                     <head>Daniel.</head>
                     <p>This Book is Hiſtorical to the Seventh Chapter, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetical in the reſt; <hi>Daniel</hi> lived at the End of the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Captivity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Hosea" type="book">
                     <head>Hoſea.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hoſea</hi> a Prophet, ſent to the Ten Tribes chiefly, compoſed this Prophecy.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Joel" type="book">
                     <head>Joel.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Joel</hi> Propheſied about the ſame time with <hi>Hoſea</hi> to the Two Tribes chiefly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Amos" type="book">
                     <head>Amos.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Amos</hi> Propheſied at the ſame time with <hi>Hoſea,</hi> and to the ſame Perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> To the Ten Tribes chiefly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Obadiah" type="book">
                     <head>Obadiah.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Obadiah</hi> foretelleth the Deſtruction of the <hi>Idumeans</hi> who came of <hi>Eſau, Jacob</hi>'s Brother.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Jonah" type="book">
                     <head>Jonah.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jonah</hi> was a Prophet in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the days of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the Second, but was ſent to <hi>Nineveh,</hi> the chief City of the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrians.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Micah" type="book">
                     <head>Micah.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Micah</hi> Propheſied at the ſame time with <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and are alike in the Subject Matter and Stile, he declares the Deſtruction of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> by the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and by the <hi>Chaldaeans.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Nahum" type="book">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:103580:36"/>
                     <head>Nahum.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nahum</hi> Propheſied of the Deſtruction of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> by the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> and <hi>Medes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Habakkuk" type="book">
                     <head>Habakkuk.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Habakkuk</hi> Propheſied of the Deſtruction of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> by the <hi>Chaldaeans;</hi> as alſo of the Puniſhment on the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> or <hi>Babylonians.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Zephaniah" type="book">
                     <head>Zephaniah.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zephaniah</hi> Propheſied but a few Years before the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and threatneth <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> with utter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Haggai" type="book">
                     <head>Haggai.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Haggai</hi> Propheſied after the 70 Years Captivity, of the <hi>Jews</hi> return from <hi>Babylon,</hi> and exhorts them to Rebuild the Temple.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Zechariah" type="book">
                     <head>Zechariah.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zechariah</hi> was ſent to confirm the Doctrine of <hi>Haggai,</hi> and to help on the Work of the Building the Temple; but his Style is more Sublime and Myſterious: He Propheſied in the Reign of <hi>Darius,</hi> in whoſe Sixth Year the Temple was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Malachi" type="book">
                     <head>Malachy.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Malachy</hi> Propheſied after the Re-edifying of the Temple, and endeth the Prophets.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="apocrypha" type="part">
                  <head>Apochryphal Books.</head>
                  <p>The word <hi>Apocryphal,</hi> ſignifies that which is hidden, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, or doubtful; Thoſe Books which carry that Title, and are bound up in our Bibles are ſo called, becauſe it is doubted whether they be True Scripture, or not certainly known to be ſo; for ſo the word in the <hi>Greek</hi> ſignifies; They are not in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> yet moſt of them are of much worth, containing many worthy Documents, and eſpecially the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> is of ſingular Uſe, for the Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the two laſt Chapters of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and part of the Second, Seventh and Eighth Chapters of that Prophet.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="New" type="Testament">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:103580:36"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> New Teſtament <hi>or</hi> Covenant.</head>
               <p>THE word in <hi>Greek</hi> which is tranſlated <hi>Teſtament,</hi> ſignifies both a <hi>Covenant</hi> and a <hi>Teſtament;</hi> a <hi>Covenant</hi> as may appear by the Adjunct <hi>New,</hi> which notes the oppoſition of This to the <hi>Old;</hi> ſo that this Book is what the <hi>Old</hi> was, not a <hi>Teſtament</hi> to which Death is ſuppoſed neceſſary, but a <hi>Covenant</hi> or <hi>Stipulation</hi> betwixt God and his People the <hi>Jews,</hi> promiſing Mercies, and requiring Duties of them.</p>
               <div type="gospels">
                  <div n="Matthew" type="book">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The Goſpel according to St.</hi> Matthew.</head>
                     <p>THE Word <hi>Goſpel</hi> comes from a <hi>Saxon</hi> word which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Spell,</hi> and is in Engliſh <hi>good Tidings</hi> (and by <hi>Euphony</hi> that is for better Sound ſake, we pronounce it <hi>Goſpel)</hi> delivered here in Hiſtory, of the <hi>Birth, Life, Actions, Precepts, Promiſes, Death, Reſurrection</hi> and <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Writers of this Hiſtory are commonly called <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> which may in general ſignifie any <hi>Preacher of the Goſpel;</hi> but is more peculiarly applied to thoſe that wrote the Hiſtory of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Life and Death,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>viz.</hi> St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi> St. <hi>Luke,</hi> St. <hi>John.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The meaning of that Phraſe, according to St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> is no more than that He compiled and ſet down that <hi>Goſpel,</hi> or good and Gladſom Word.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Mark" type="book">
                     <head>
                        <hi>St.</hi> Mark.</head>
                     <p>St. <hi>Mark</hi>'s Goſpel was dictated by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe Diſciple, Amanuenſis or Scribe St. <hi>Mark</hi> was.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="Luke" type="book">
                     <head>
                        <hi>St.</hi> Luke.</head>
                     <p>St. <hi>Luke</hi> was the Diſciple and Follower of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who wrote this <hi>Goſpel</hi> and the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="John" type="book">
                     <head>
                        <hi>St.</hi> John.</head>
                     <p>St. <hi>John,</hi> the beloved Apoſtle, wrote this <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="epistles">
                  <head>The Epiſtles.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Epiſtles</hi> were written by thoſe that bear their Name, <hi>viz.</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> St. <hi>Jude,</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle, by whom the <hi>Apocalypſe</hi> or the <hi>Revelation</hi> was wrote alſo.</p>
                  <div n="Hebrews" type="book">
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:103580:37"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>Epiſtle to the</hi> Hebrews.</head>
                     <p>Whether the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> was written by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> hath not only of Late, but Anciently been doubted; And as the Title which is in our Copy (pretending not to be a part of the Epiſtle) is not ſufficient to conclude any more, Than that it was in that time when this Title was prefix'd believed to be St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s: So there is no doubt but that it went without any Superſcription or Known Author more Anciently, and ſo has left ſome place to Variety of Conjectures who the Author ſhould be? Some Father it on St. <hi>Barnabas,</hi> ſome on <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> others on St. <hi>Luke,</hi> the latter very Learned Men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for, from the Obſervation of the Stile and Idiom; But all that can be ſaid can amount to no higher than to Probable or Conjectural: And 'tis not Matter of any weight or Neceſſity that it be defined who the Author was, whether St. <hi>Paul</hi> or St. <hi>Luke,</hi> a conſtant Companion of his for many Years, and the Author of two other Books of the Sacred Canon.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:103580:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
